<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The new birth, or, Birth from above presented in foure sermons in Margarets Westminister, December 25 and January 15, 1653 and June 11, 1654 / by Edward Tharpe.</title>
            <author>Tharpe, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T838A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26290</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09411718</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09411718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1317:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The new birth, or, Birth from above presented in foure sermons in Margarets Westminister, December 25 and January 15, 1653 and June 11, 1654 / by Edward Tharpe.</title>
                  <author>Tharpe, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Webbe and Will. Grantham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEW BIRTH: OR, BIRTH FROM ABOVE. Preſented in Foure Sermons in <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter, December,</hi> 25. and <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 15. 1653. and <hi>June</hi> 11. 1654.</p>
            <p>By EDVVARD THARPE, Miniſter of the Word at <hi>Street</hi> in <hi>Somerſet</hi>-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ideo Filius Dei factus eſt homo, ut homines faceret Filius Dei.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Non naſcimur, ſed renaſcimur Chriſtiani.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 COR. 5. 17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>JOHN 3. 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, except a man be borne from above, he cannot ſee the Kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath: Webbe,</hi> and <hi>Will: Grantham,</hi> at the black Bear in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the little North door. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNESSE, <hi>OLIVER,</hi> Lord Protector of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot long ſince attending upon your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe and the ſick bed of your Deare and Noble Mother (who hath lived to ſee you as high in the world as ever you were in her tender &amp; careful thoughts) with a Heart and a Tongue full of duty and thankfulneſs; as for your firſt favours in my child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, wherein I taſted deeply of your goodneſſe, ſo for your laſt timely favour now in my Age, wherein I taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in part of your goodneſſe and greatneſſe together. And taking a ſolemne and ſubmiſſive leave of your Highneſſe, I entred into ſome ſerious conſideration (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto moved by your free, noble, and benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent expreſſions (which indeed my Lord did ſilently command me to ſpeak again) how I might expreſſe to your Highneſſe, and manifeſt to the world ſome appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent teſtimony, as of my gratitude to you, (now ſitting at the ſterne) ſo of my improvement under you in the Univerſity: And therefore immediately after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from you (in <hi>December</hi> laſt) my pains being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired in <hi>Margarets Weſtm.</hi> and willingly and readily accepted, and as well approved as accepted by ſome worthy and judicious Auditors, I was ſeriouſly impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned
<pb facs="tcp:43024:3"/> and ſolicited for the Notes: Which opportunity, with ſome difficulty I waved, fearing if communicated they might ſteale to the Preſſe, and ſo being but mean and inconſiderable in themſelves, unworthy of ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, being likewiſe imperfect and unperuſed, they might by the haſty printing of them be made worſe: And being perſwaded, that your Lordſhip might heare ſomething of them, I am bold, moſt Noble Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving viewed and digeſted them, <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>between hope &amp; fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Humillima cordis &amp; corporis inclinatione,</hi> to dedicate them to your Highneſſe, and to ſet them forth in your Lordſhips name.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was by your Lordſhips means, or your much honoured Mothers, (my worthy and noble Friend and Lady) that I was ever made capable of any Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promotion, or entred into this ſacred and holy Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being ſent by her &amp; your moſt worthy Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that well deſerving and eſteemed Patriot, long ſince with the Lord) to wait upon your Highneſſe in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> where and at whoſe feet I did imbibe ſuch principles, as have in a meane and moderate way inabled me to carry ſome of that light which ſhone gloriouſly there, and in ſome ſplendour in <hi>Sidney Suſsex</hi> Colledge, where your Highneſſe was a Fellow-Commoner and Student (under a godly, learned, and reverend Maſter) into the world. So that next to God, I owe my ſelfe, (and the beſt of my ſelfe, my Labours) unto you (my Lord) <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuum eſt fateri per qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fecimus,</hi> and I am in very good hope your Highneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will pleaſe to taſte of the fruit of that tree which was of your owne planting, (though the fruit be not ſo exquiſite and pleaſant as that which had a warmer and longer influence) and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffer it to wither, or be pull'd up by the roots.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:3"/>
            <p n="3">3. They were framed under your Highneſſe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and therefore by another right they juſtly claime your tuition; and if there be any good at all in them, it is to be aſcribed (next unto Him who is the Giver of every good and perfect gift) to your Highneſſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which procured me thoſe quiet,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> peaceable, and ſilent houres, in the which they were compoſed.</p>
            <p>Such therefore as theſe rude Meditations are, I moſt humbly preſent and dedicate to your Highneſs, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeeching you to credit them &amp; me with your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious favour and benevolent aſpect, under whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance they will certainly finde eaſie acceptance, and may doe ſome good abroad.</p>
            <p>Thus with my fervent, frequent, and conſtant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for your Highneſſe, that you may doe as you doe, (and have promiſed to doe) make it your work to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him who hath ſo highly advanced you, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfie the expections of many thouſands of people, eſpecially ours of the Clergy, whoſe eyes are upon you for good, our calling being once honourable, (and ſo we hope by your meanes it may be againe) and we may live to ſee <hi>Trajan</hi>'s dayes, in whoſe time they ſay a good man never wanted, nor a learned man beg'd: (For ſurely they will honour Learning, whoſe actions require and deſerve a learned pen) though it be now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and abuſed by many ignorants, faring herein like the Maſter of the calling, who in ſuch eyes had neither forme nor beauty. It was a <hi>Jeroboam</hi> my Lord) you know that made Prieſts of the loweſt of the people, (which makes him carry that infamous brand and train nineteene times after him in Scripture) <hi>Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat, &amp;c.</hi> by committing and impoſing the truſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Gods ſacred Oracles into ſuch uncleane and unholy
<pb facs="tcp:43024:4"/> hands, and now the loweſt of the people make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Prieſts; This braſſe coyne, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> cals them, bearing their owne ſtampe and impreſſion. And it is not unknowne to your Highneſſe, that the deſpiſing of the Ephod was the rot of <hi>Sauls</hi> Kingdome: That Iſrael was without God, when it was without a Prieſt to teach: That faithfull Paſtours and teachers are the guard, the ſafe-guard, the life-guard of a Church and State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſo by a King, and enemy to Sion: That it was great <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s word to his Clergy, <hi>Adjuvate me precibus, ego vos gladio;</hi> Help me with your prayers, I will help you with my power. That pious and devout Lord in this Land and Common-wealth, accounted the prayers of faithful Miniſters the walls of his houſe.</p>
            <p>Let it be the ſhame, and indelible blot of the Romiſh Synagogue, the Malignant Church, to have Golden Chalices and Wooden Prieſts, Mendicant and begging Prieſts, or their Prieſts beggars. It is the honour and dignity of a Chriſtian Magiſtracy &amp; Common-wealth, when and where they that labour in the Word &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, are accounted worthy of double honour, and have both countenance and maintenance, regard and reward. I moſt humbly kiſſe your hand, (for an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, ſhould not fill the hand) craving pardon for my prolixity &amp; preſumption, which I hope, good my Lord, having had ſome early experience of your Highneſſe candour and condeſcention you will eaſily grant, accounting it my great happineſſe that ever I had any dependance upon you, and my honour and credit to have been, and to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(My Lord)</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Oratour, and at your Highneſſe command and ſervice, <hi>Edward Tharpe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> May be by ſome wondred at, for ſending ſuch rude and unpoliſhed lines to the Preſſe, which even groanes under the burden of multitude of bookes; of the greater part whereof we may ſay with <hi>Socrates,</hi> The Paper is more worth than the matter: For there are ſcarce any that Preach that Print not, inſomuch as the Preſſe may ſay to the Pulpit in the words of <hi>Eſau</hi> to his brother, <hi>Keep that thou haſt, I have enough my brother.</hi> And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it may be objected, that I make too much uſe of other mens ſentences and ſenſe, and ſo ſeeme to boaſt in other mens lines made ready to my hands: To whom I anſwer no otherwiſe, than As the Spiders fine web is never the better, (it may be the ſooner ſwept away) becauſe it is ſpun out of her owne bowels; So the Bees honey is never the leſſe (it may be the more) ſweet, becauſe it is extracted and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of many flowers. Thirdly, I hope the ſubject will make an eaſie way for the acceptance, treating of a through change and reformation. And it is to be hoped and deſired, nay expected, that amongst ſo many changes and mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which have been abroad in the great world, Man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that little world, will not ſtill remaine quite unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For where Gods judgements are out in the world, the Prophet gives it as granted Gods people will learne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Againe, howſoever art may move affection, it is the plain Word in the evidence and power thereof which must remove corruption. Fourthly, I could adde, they were
<pb facs="tcp:43024:5"/> preached in a very populous, orthodox, and judicious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, and deſired earnestly of men of judgment and note, of worth and parts, whoſe reſpects I have rather ſatisfied in the printing of them, than mine owne deſires. Beſides, I have not read any that have ſo fully treated or diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of this materiall and neceſſary ſubject; and therefore I requeſt every Reader in the words of <hi>Iſocrates</hi> to <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Aut hiſce praeceptis utere, aut tu ipſe inveni meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora:</hi> Either make uſe of theſe wholſome Doctrines and Exhortations with me, or elſe publiſh better thy ſelfe; if thou art able to publiſh better in the future, yet it will profit thee to make uſe of theſe for the preſent. I am bold therefore for the reaſons aforeſaid to ſend that to the eye which was at firſt preſented to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are; hoping that ſome way or other they may get to the heart, and with <hi>Naamans</hi> poore ſervants ſend ſome to that <hi>Jordan</hi> which may cure them of their native leproſie. Which that theſe diſtracted Meditations may help to do, I leave and commend thee in my prayers and devotions to God, and to the word of his grace, which, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 32. So prayes,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy ſervant in Jeſus Chriſt, EDWARD THARPE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <bibl>HORAT.</bibl>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Si quid noviſti rectius iſt is,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candidus imperti: ſi non, his utere mecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Reader, if better things be knowne to thee,</l>
               <l>Impart them, or make uſe of theſe with me.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43024:5"/>
            <head>THE HEAVENLY BIRTH: OR, BIRTH from ABOVE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JAM. 1. 18.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of his own will begat he us by the word of truth, that we ſhould be a kind of firſt fruits of his creatures.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His General Epiſtle of St. <hi>James</hi> ſo called, not becauſe it is more general, or authentick than other of the Epiſtles (all being of equal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſs) but in regard of the dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (it being directed and dedicated to the twelve diſperſed Tribes, <hi>ver.</hi> 1.) is full of very uſefull, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall doctrin, eſpecially this firſt Chapter; which treates of divers Graces and Virtues, and preſſes many heavenly precepts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It perſwades to comfort in afflictions, nay even to joy in tribulation, and that by a ſweet, loving, and inſinuating com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation (<hi>My brethren:) James</hi> was the Brother of our Lord, and for his virtues and holineſs called, <hi>James the juſt:</hi> yet out of Apoſtolical kindneſs and humility, that his exhortations might be the more prevalent and perſwaſive, being ſeaſoned with meekneſs and love he calls them <hi>Brethren; My brethren</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> 
               <hi>count it all joy when you fall into divers temptations.</hi> That is, eſteem it matter of chief joy and exultation to tread in their <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 12.</note> Maſters ſteps: <hi>Rejoyce, and be glad; for,</hi> &amp;c. This leſſon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> learnt out of the School of the Croſs, who <hi>went away</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 5. 41.</note> 
               <hi>rejoycing that they were counted worthy</hi> &amp;c. The birds of Paradiſe ſing ſweeteſt in a cage, knowing that to them it is given (as a great bleſſing) not onely to beleeve, but to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake; and that <hi>through many tribulations we muſt enter into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Philip. 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi> The more we ſuffer, the liker Chriſt;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43024:6"/> and the longer, the greater will be our reward.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly: In the two next verſes it exhorts to Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, the two Legs of Chriſtianity, the two ſupporters under the croſs; the onely cordials in heavy and calamitous times (ſuch as thoſe were.) For Faith beleeves the promiſes, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience attends and waits for the accompliſhment; and indeed, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We have need of patience,</hi> that when we have done the will of God, (in doing whereof we ſhall find great <note place="margin">Heb 10. 27.</note> oppoſition) wee may receive the promiſe. Faith holds up a Chriſtians head, but Patience and Perſeverance crowns it: He that beleeves makes not haſt; for he knows that in good time <hi>he ſhall reap, if he faint not. Knowing that the tryall of your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>faith,</hi> &amp;c. And, <hi>let patience have her perfect work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nature of Afflictions is, they are probations and tryals. The effect of them, they work Patience, they bring the quiet <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 11.</note> fruit of righteouſneſs to them that are exerciſed therein.</p>
            <p>The fineſt Gold is put into the hotteſt furnace; witneſs the three children: <hi>Peter</hi>'s faith was tryed by Sathans winnowing, and <hi>Paul</hi>'s by his buffeting; but Chriſts prayer was ſufficient for the one, and his grace for the other: And the Son of God walks with his children even in the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt fire, and reſtrains the heat and flames. Therefore whatſoever our ſufferings are, we ought to kiſs Gods rod, and to embrace his chaſtiſements upon our knees; like the Camel, to take our load ſtooping, and not to make thoſe afflictions which are bitter enough of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelves, to be far more bitter by our impatience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the 5, 6, 7, and 8 verſes the Apoſtle directs us how we ſhould direct our prayers to God, that we may ſpeed in our ſuits, and not be ſent empty away. <hi>If any man want wiſdom,</hi> that is, the wiſdom to behave himſelf quietly and Chriſtianly under Gods correcting hand (which requires great wiſdom and prudence: A Chriſtian being ſo much a Chriſtian as he is in temptations and tryals) <hi>let him ask of God, who gives to all men liberally, and upbraids not,</hi> &amp;c. But let him look to the manner of his asking which God regards more then the matter, looking not ſo much at the thing, and duty done, as at the mind and affection with which it is done: regarding not ſo much <hi>quam bonum</hi> as <hi>quam bene;</hi> looking more at the heart then the hand:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43024:6"/> 
               <hi>My ſon give me thy heart. Let him ask in faith nothing waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> They muſt be confident in then petitions, the heart muſt be firmly ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led upon Gods promiſes without any doubting or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vering: For the crue, and effectuall prayer is the prayer of <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 28</note> Faith: <hi>Whatſoever ye ask in prayer beleeve and you ſhall receive it.</hi> This was that made thoſe Jews prayers miſcarry, they <note place="margin">James 4. 4.</note> were unmannerly and ſenſuall: <hi>Ye ask, and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs, that ye might ſpend it upon your luſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In the 9th verſe it teacheth the man of low degree how to carry himſelf under the burden of his poverty anu want, ſo as to have an eye to his exaltation; <hi>Let the brother of low degree rejoice that he is exalted.</hi> Bleſs God with <hi>Job</hi> as well when he takes away, as when he gives. Gods own dear chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are often placed in the loweſt formes: but here is their comfort, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n may be baſe and low, in a mean<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and deſpicable condition in the eye of the world, and yet be high in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; who looks not as man looks, man at the habit, God at the heart. Though he be <hi>re pauper, ſpe dives,</hi> a poor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may be arich Saint: Rich in inward, and ſpiritual endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and qualifications, which alone God values. And many times a man hath moſt of theſe riches, when he hath leaſt of the others; <hi>Peter</hi> had no ſilver nor gold, but he had that power from above to cure the criple which ſilver and gold could not <note place="margin">James 2. 5. Mat. 5. 3.</note> doe. And <hi>God</hi> (as <hi>James</hi> ſaith) <hi>hath choſen the poor of the world rich in faith, and heirs of his kingdom.</hi> Nay, he muſt be poor in ſpirit who expects that kingdom. A poor man may be (nay often is) heir to a heavenly kingdom: If he be as poor in ſpirit as he is in purſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It teacheth a man of high degree, a rich man how to carry himſelf upon his mountain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not to think with <hi>Babylon</hi> never to be moved and ſhaken, but in his greateſt height and altitude <note place="margin">Ver. 10. 11.</note> to think and fear he may be brought down: But <hi>let the rich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice that he is brought low<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or made low, becauſe as the flower of the graſs he ſhall paſs away: For the ſun no ſooner riſeth with a burning heat but it withereth the graſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the flower thereof fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the grace and faſhion thereof periſheth; ſo alſo ſhall,</hi> &amp;c. In which two verſes we ſee that all humane things ſtand upon two lame legs, Incertainty, and Inſufficiency, or unſatisfaction.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43024:7"/> They are uncertain to continue, and unſufficient to content. Their eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the ear with hearing. Again, he that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver: <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2. 8.</note> They are uncertain too; truſt not in uncertain riches but in the living God; and <hi>if riches increaſe ſet not your hearts upon them.</hi> How doth St. <hi>James</hi> in thoſe two verſes ſhadow out the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and frail condition of all worldly luſtre? Even Scepters and Diadems have their periods, and the greateſt Preferments, and Honours upon earth their appointed dates, Empires and Crowns have their mutations and alterations, their trepidations and terminations, and like other inferiour bodies their growth, declining and expiring. Two deadly enemies doe alwaies at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all earthly Crowns, Death, and Diſturbance; the one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowns the head, or, the other un-heads the crown. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing permanent, nothing ſure or certain under the Sun, nor will be in this wayning, and waxing Moon, until with the true faithfull ſonnes of our Mother (the Church) we have this <note place="margin">Revel. 12. 1, 2.</note> Moon, this world under our feet, and be cloathed with that Sun of righteouſneſs which never ſets, and crowned with that Crown which Chriſt the juſt Judge ſhall ſet upon the head of them which fight his battails, and follow the doctrine of the twelve Apoſtles (which do indeed imbelliſh that Crown.) Let not the rich therefore grieve or pine that they are brought low; becauſe as the flower of the graſs they ſhall paſs away, ſo eaſily, and ſo ſurely. The lowneſſe of mans mould ſhould therefore take down the highneſſe of his mind; and the conſideration of his frail and fading eſtate, be a ſtrong motive to humility and lowlyneſs: Neither beauty, nor honour, nor riches, nor pomp, nor power, nor any outward ſplendour and luſtre, ſhould, or doe elate a true and wel-grounded Chriſtian, but ſeriouſly pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the vain, frail, and fading condition of all theſe, he will withdraw his heart from an high eſteem of all excellencies and greatneſs; live in a conſtant, and continuall expectation of, and preparation for a change.</p>
            <p>Note this wel I pray you you who pride your ſelves in earthly honours, beauties and worldly braveries: All fleſh is graſs, and the glory, the goodneſs, the beauty, and comelineſs as the flower of the graſs. The flower is the beauty of the graſs, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43024:7"/> beauty and favour are the flowers of the fleſh, but both fade <note place="margin">Note.</note> and wither. All fleſh is ſo; the faireſt, the comelieſt, the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt, the higheſt, and ſtrongeſt, the honourableſt: It is not only graſs which continueth longeſt, but as the beauty and flower of the graſs which fades ſooneſt; for the graſs often ſtands and remains when the flowers are cropt and withered. And it is worth your noting too, to bring you unto the love and longing after another birth, which my Text treats of, How ſoon the flower fades, withers, and miſcarries. The hand crops it, or the worm eats it, or the ſun ſcorcheth it, or the wind blaſteth it, or the froſt pincheth it, or elſe thoſe timely and early bloſſoms fall off of themſelves, as <hi>May</hi> flowers. How ſoon I pray you do all earthly beauties and honours like flowers fade and wither? Even as ſoon almoſt as they are diſplayed, they do but open and ſhew themſelves, and are gone and vaniſhed; juſt like <hi>Jonah's</hi> Gourd, doth come up in an night, and withered in a day: The Sun doth but ſhine, as the Apoſtle ſaith, with a ſcorching heat, and they wither; they, and their riches, and honour, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and power, paſſe, and are gone, and that with as eaſie a turn, and motion of providence as the flower fades. All is vanity, and it were well if men felt not the other, vexation of ſpirit. This was excellently, and elegantly figured, and ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 30, 31.</note> in <hi>Nebuchadnezar's</hi> Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. which had a head of fine gold, and breaſt and arms of ſilver, thighs of braſs, and legs of iron, but his feet were of duſt and clay. The higheſt, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt, the nobleſt, the ſtrongeſt, let them carry their heads never ſo high with <hi>Babel</hi> (the hammer of the world) build their neſts in the clouds, or higher amongſt the ſtars, and (in vain confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) boaſt with her, <hi>I ſit as a Queen and ſhall never be moved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> yet they go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all upon feet of dirt and clay, which will quickly fail them, and lay their honour in the duſt: Though they have golden beginnings, and proſperous, and ſuccesfull proceedings, long, and ſtrong continuance, yet theſe great bodies are mortall too, they goe the ſame way as ſmall ones doe, onely they make a greater noiſe in their riſe and fall: They have their beginning and ending, their infancy, youth and age, as thoſe great Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies had prefigured in that great Image: For God ſets them their bounds, as he doth to the ſea, which they cannot paſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43024:8"/> and ſaith to them (as to that) Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no further, here will I ſtop thy proud waves: But in this new Birth, this Birth from above of which my Text treats, we are begotten from above by a Father to an Inheritance immortall, and undefiled, which fades not away, and to a Kingdom which cannot be ſhaken, as all worldly Kingdomes are.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the 12. verſe the Apoſtle ſhews the happy and bleſſed <note place="margin">Ver. 12.</note> condition of affliction patiently born, they terminate, and end in happyneſs: In much ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rance is eaſe, and the Croſs leads to the Crown: Affliction and Bleſſedneſs do often meet in the ſame perſon; an afflicted man is a bleſſed man, if he deſpiſe not the chaſtening and correction of the Lord, but patiently, and willingly welcome it, with the words of <hi>Jerem. It is my ſorrow, and I will bear it. Bleſſed is the man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The 13, 14, 15, 16 verſes ſet forth unto us the true Father of a falſe child: The child is ſin; the father, with ſome, is in ſome controverſis: For as notorious, and common Strumpets doe ſome times lay their Baſtards at the Church door, ſo there are ſome prophane, and Atheiſtical perſons which lay their ſin and iniquity at heaven gates, and would make God the author of ſin: Which the Apoſtle takes away in the four former mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned verſes: <hi>Let no man when he is tempted, ſay, I am tempted of God; for God tempts no man to evill, neither is tempted: But every man is tempted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>God is no wayes to be thought the Parent of ſuch a baſe brat: For as <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> ſurely <hi>Deus non poteſt eſſe illius author cujus eſt ultor;</hi> God cannot be the author of that which he is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger. To make a hell, and to caſt into that hell, ſtands not with the Nature, Wiſdome and Mercy of God: This falſe, and erroneous opinion the Apoſtle takes away in the 16 verſe; <hi>Erre not dear brethren.</hi> We ſhould be dear to one another, though divided; <hi>Dear,</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> in affection, though divided in opinion: For, <hi>It is a good and joyfull thing for</hi> &amp;c. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <note place="margin">Pſal. 13 3.</note> you erre in other things, let not this damnable error ſo far poſſeſs you, as to make God the author of ſin. Miſtake not ſo far as to ſay, Becauſe God concurs in ſin, the action of ſin, he hath any hand in the evill of it: Nor ſay, If God would not have me ſin, why doth he not hinder me? The action indeed is
<pb facs="tcp:43024:8"/> Gods, becauſe in him we live, move, and have our being: But <note place="margin">Acts 14.</note> the evill of the action that is Sathans, and our own. The devill is the father, and ſin his own, no other mother then our own luſts. Indeed nothing is ſo truly ours as our ſin, which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough by our cockering of it, and our indulgence over it, and by our lothneſs to part with it: we dandle it, and hug it, and feed and foſter it, and cry with the Harlot, <hi>Ne dividatur,</hi> Let it not be divided, let that live though ſaid ſhe, although it be an eye-ſore to God, and a plague-ſore to the ſoul; and if we kill not ſin in us, then ſin in us will kill us: Yet many men will part from their ſouls rather than their ſin. How comes it elſe to paſs, that Hell hath ſo many ſouls, if their ſin was not dearer to them than their ſouls?</p>
            <p>Man is the active author, God the permitter, and ſufferer of ſin: God ſuſtaines the motion of the will, man he defiles, and pollutes the act of willing: God conforms and agrees to the action, men to the pravity and deformity of the action. As darkneſſe neceſſarily follows when the Sun withdraws his light, and yet the Sun is not the cauſe of the darkneſſe, but the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the light; ſo when God withdraws his grace ſin fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, but not as an effect, the cauſe, but as a conſequent to the Antecedent: Therefore, <hi>erre not my dear brethren;</hi> God is ſo far from being the author of ſin, that he is the fountain and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> originall of all graces and virtues. Verſe 17. <hi>Every good</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Noſtra bona ſunt Dei dona;</hi> Our goods are from his goodneſs; they are the enumerations and rayes of that <hi>Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Then comes in the Text; for from whence doth every good and perfect gift proceed, but from the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the good will and pleaſure of God,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the fountain and original of all Graces and goodneſs?</p>
            <p>This is the Inference, and Coherence of the words; wherein if I have been too tedious, and intrenched upon your patience: If I have made too long and large an entry or porch to ſo ſmall a houſe, pardon my boldneſs my intent was to bring in my Text in order and method: Let us now look into that houſe we all deſire to be of, and in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his own will he begat us with the word of truth, that we ſhould be as the firſt fruits of his creatures.</hi> With reflection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43024:9"/> of your eyes to the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, which is more remote, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, which is more near, and to which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the words of my Text have relation: Conſider, I pray you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that of all thoſe gifts and graces which God of his free love hath given to the children of men; of all thoſe evidences and teſtimonies of Gods good will and pleaſure, of all thoſe divine expr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſions of his goodneſs and mercy, this of our New Birth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Birth from above is the greateſt, and chiefeſt. Of our R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>generation I ſay again, or ſecond Birth: For man in his firſt birth, <hi>Man born of a woman hath but a ſhort time to live, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 14. 1.</note> 
               <hi>is full of miſerie.</hi> His life (poor man) is not ſhort and ſweet, but ſhort and ſharp: though he hath want of daies, yet he hath ſtore of miſeries. And miſerable he is, not onely in regard of the calamities and ſorrows he is born to, but in regard of the ſin, and iniquity he is born in: For being firſt <hi>ab immundo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptus ſemine,</hi> born of unclean ſeed, and nurſed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull womb, <hi>ubi prius incipit macula quam vita,</hi> where he is ſtained and polluted before he be conceived or quickned. How can that be clean which is born of a Woman? <hi>I was born in iniquity</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) and in ſin hath my mother conceived me.</hi> As if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 51. 5.</note> had ſaid, True it is, O Lord, and I doe freely, and feelingly confeſs it, that I have been over-ſpread with corruption ever ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce I ſaw the light: Nay, which is more, no ſooner was the ſubſtances whereof I was framed and made, warm in my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb, but I was ſtained and tainted with originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Therefore v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry neceſſary and needfull is a new, and another Birth to cover the ſtains and pollutions of the firſt, of the old: A ſecond birth to ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie our firſt; a birth from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove to make holy our naturall birth; Regeneration to bleſs our Generation; as neceſſary and needfull as light is unto darkneſs, as heaven to the immunity and freedom from hell, as reparation to a ruinous and rotten building, as the ſoul to give life unto the body. Nay ſo neceſſary and needfull, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it we cannot ſee the Kingdome of God. <hi>Verily, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you, that I had two births my ſelf, one by an eternall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>generation, which no man can declare: Another in the fulneſs of time being made of a woman,</hi> &amp;c. You muſt have two births too, <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 4.</note> one from Heaven, or your earthly and carnall birth can doe you no good.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43024:9"/>
            <p>The <hi>Italians</hi> have a prudent proverb, it is good to be born<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſe, or twice; wiſe no man can be borne, <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> naſcitur ſummus,</hi> or <hi>ſanctus.</hi> No man is borne a Saint, but made ſo, <hi>virtus non eſt ex traduce,</hi> goodneſſe is not by generation, it muſt be therefore by regeneration: Better a thouſand times not be borne at all, than not borne againe; we ſhall very bitterly curſe the day of our firſt Birth, if we have not a ſecond. Many ſolemnize &amp; keep feſtival their Birth-day (which they have little reaſon to doe, if they looke upon their Birth-ſinne.) If their naturall condition be conſidered, they have little cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce or be merry upon their Birth-day, it calls rather to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation or Teares. The new borne Babe ſeems to cry down that joy and exaltation, who comes crying into a troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſt.</hi>
               </note> world. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndum naſcitur ſed proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tat,</hi> It is the day and bleſſed time of our New Birth, wherein we ſhould rejoyce and be glad, which we ſhould keep holy to the Lord, wherein as in our Baptiſme (the Laver, and Seale, and Signe of regeneration as in our earthly Regiſters) our names are written in the book of life, wherein we are borne to live for ever; whereas in our Birth we are <hi>damnati antequam nati,</hi> damned before we be borne: being <hi>filii terrae</hi> we are <hi>filii irae,</hi> we muſt therefore be <hi>renati,</hi> if we would not be <hi>damnati,</hi> renewed and converted, if we will not be condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> From which conſideration, take this obſervation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Doctrine; <hi>He that is borne twice, ſhall dye but once, but he that is but once borne ſhall dye twice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Birth ſhall free us from the ſecond Death, the firſt, and none but that, ſhall make us liable both to the firſt and to the ſecond death: But what doe I ſay, that the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate perſon the Beleever ſhall dye? no, he ſhall not dye at all: <hi>Quicunque ſermones m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s cuſtodiverint,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Whoſoever keeps my ſayings, he ſhall not taste, he ſhall not ſee death.</hi> Death may buz and keepe a noiſe about his eares like an angry Waſp, but he hath loſt his ſting, the ſting was left in Chriſt Jeſus body, he doth victoriouſly triumph over it; <hi>O Death where is thy ſting? O Grave,</hi> &amp;c. He may exult and rejoyce over Death; O Death, my Saviour hath been thy death, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u canſt not be mine: My Saviour dyed for me, I cannot dye by thee:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43024:10"/> Chriſt hath killed thee, and thou canſt not kill me; if kill me, not hurt me. I have made my peace with my Judge, and I feare not the Baily; my Redeemer hath made my peace with my God, and being juſtified by Faith, I have my <hi>Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus eſt,</hi> I have peace with God, and therefore neither Death, nor Hell, nor he that hath the power of both can hurt me; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to every regenerate perſon I may pronounce that bleſſing, which Saint <hi>John</hi> doth, to them that have part in the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (which is nothing elſe but regeneration.) <hi>Bleſſed and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 20, 6.</note> 
               <hi>holy is he that hath his part in the firſt reſurrection;</hi> for on ſuch the ſecond <hi>Death ſhall have no power, but they ſhall be as Kings and Priests unto God:</hi> Of this ſupernaturall and Heavenly B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth doth this birth treat, and of all the 4. cauſes thereof. 1. The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, 2. The Efficient, 3. The Inſtrumentall, and 4. the Final cauſe. 1. The formal cauſe &amp; that is God, <hi>progenuit D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> God begets us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Efficient, that is his will, he begets us of his will; for why he ſaves one and not another, why he ſoftens this wax upon which he will inſtamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Image, and why he hardens that clay, which he will caſt away, there is no reaſon can be given hereof, but the good pleaſure of his will; <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18. <hi>He will have mercy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Inſtrumentall cauſe is <hi>verbum veritatis,</hi> the word of truth, called ſo for 4. Reaſons. 1. Becauſe it hath God, the God of Truth for its Author. 2. Becauſe it hath Chriſt the Truth it ſelfe, for its Witneſſe: 3. Becauſe it hath the Spirit of Truth for its compoſer; and 4. Becauſe it teacheth all truth, and leads into all truth: <hi>I will pray to the Father, and he ſhall ſend the ſpirit of truth, which ſhall lead or guide you into all truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word of Truth is the ſeed of our New Birth, <hi>By the grace of God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, I have begotten you by the Goſpell,</hi> where you have againe the inſtrument, the meanes and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, the Inſtrument, I <hi>Paul</hi> for though you have ten thouſand inſtructors, <hi>I am your Father in Chriſt,</hi> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The meanes, the Goſpel or Word, the Author Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe word it is, and who himſelfe is the ſupreame worke in our regeneration.</p>
            <p>Then fourthly, here is the finall cauſe why we are regenerate and borne againe to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy and ſanctified, to be as the firſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43024:10"/> fruits of his Creatures, <hi>i. e.</hi> that as amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Law, the firſt fruits were conſecrate and ſet apart for God, ſo rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate perſons and believers amongſt and above all others are ſequeſtred and ſet apart for the ſervices and purpoſes of God; and this end and effect of Regeneration, ſhews the Honour and Dignity, the priviledge and prerogatives of the ſonnes of God, as you ſhall here anon; otherwiſe as in other Births, ſo in this you may pleaſe to obſerve 4. things more. 1. <hi>Partus.</hi> 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi> 3. <hi>Semen.</hi> And 4. <hi>Fructus.</hi> The Birth, the Womb, the Seed, and the Fruit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Partus.</hi>
               </note> The Birth, and that is a holy Birth, <hi>prog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nuit Deus,</hi> God begets us. The Spirit of the Almighty over-ſhadowing the Soul, as it did the Body of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> ſanctifies it, and begets a new Creature; for as Chriſt was conceived by the holy Ghoſt, ſo muſt every Chriſtian be.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vterus.</hi>
               </note> The Womb, and that is a holy Womb too, the Womb of the Morne, as <hi>David</hi> calls it, the dew of thy Birth is &amp;c. or <note place="margin">Pſal. 110 3.</note> thy Birth from the Womb is as the morning dew, (a holy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the words) which enlivens and exhilerates all things, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Andr.</hi>
               </note> refreſhes and renews them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Semen.</hi>
               </note> Here is <hi>Semen,</hi> the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and that is a holy ſeed too, <hi>We are borne,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>not of mortall, but immortall, not of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible but incorruptible ſeed, even of the word,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. A ſeed which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls living, both becauſe it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns them that are dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, and becauſe it makes us heires of eternall life. <note place="margin">Note.</note> A ſeed cleane contrary to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſeed, for as that begets ſinfull man, this kills him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Fructus.</hi>
               </note> Laſtly, here is <hi>Fructus</hi> the fruit, and that is a holy and heavenly fruit too; for being regenerate and borne againe unto God <hi>We have,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>our fruit unto holineſſe, and the end is everlaſting life,</hi> Rom. 6. 21.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee in part, the nature, manner, cauſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct, and end of our New Birth, or Birth from above.</p>
            <p>This unto fleſh and blood ſeems very ſtrange; tell the natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al man of his regeneration, and new Birth, that he muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be borne againe, and you ſpeake to him a parable and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. You can never faſten any thing upon him, but what is made evident by demonſtration: He will not believe that he ſees not, and therefore certainly he ſhall never ſee that which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43024:11"/> he cannot or will not believe: As <hi>Nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> before his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion hearing Chriſt ſpeak of the neceſſity of Regeneration, he makes it a matter of impoſſibility; <hi>How can a man be borne when he is old, can he enter into his Mothers wombe and be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> A ſtrange, nay, an impoſſible thing he thinks it is, to be borne againe, by the word or ſpirit of God: Words thinks he, may beget words (as they doe too often) but not creatures. And that <hi>Poſthumus</hi> ſhould be <hi>Primitiae,</hi> the laſt creature made the firſt fruits, this ſeems altogether impoſſible: But Faith is not captivated to ſence, it exceeds reaſons limits, it is not the Naturall, but the Spirituall man. Nor the Naturall but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eye, which diſcernes how God is our Father.</p>
            <p>Indeed many wayes doth the Lord challenge unto himſelfe this loving attribute of Paternity and Fatherhood, but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally three: 1. By Creation, 2. By Regeneration, and 3. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption; Between which there are theſe differences in our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We were <hi>filii facti,</hi> made Sons; In our regeneration we are <hi>filii geniti,</hi> begotten Sonnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Creation, that was out of Gods councell, <hi>Faciamus hominem,</hi> let us make man after our Image.</p>
            <p>Our regeneration, that is, out of his will, <hi>voluntariè nos genuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In our Creation; <hi>Dixit Dens &amp; formati ſumus,</hi> God ſpake the word, and we were formed and made; in our Regeneration, <hi>Operatur Spiritus Sanctus &amp; reformati ſumus,</hi> Gods ſpirit works, and we are reformed, re-made.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In our Creation he gave us our ſelves; in our regeneration, he gave himſelfe for us, his life for us: He gave his ſoule a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſinne, that he might <hi>ſee his ſeed, Eſay.</hi> 53. 10.</p>
            <p>Our Creation as I hinted, coſt him but a few words, he ſpake and we were made, he commanded and it was effected: But our Redemption through his blood, coſt him many words and blows, many wounds and ſufferings, that he might ſee his ſeed he made his ſoule an offernig for ſinne; He took upon him our ſinnes that we might be taken for Sonnes.</p>
            <p>We were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> by our generation in <hi>Adam</hi> we all dye, but in Chriſt we are all made alive.</p>
            <p>We fell in <hi>Adam,</hi> and his fall hath wounded and bruiſed us,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43024:11"/> but <hi>Chriſti liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſanati ſumus,</hi> by Chriſts ſtripes we are heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. A ſtrange way to be healed by wounding. To kill the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to recover the Patient: That God ſhould dye, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve man from death: To tame a Lyon, they ſay they beate a Dogge, but here the Lyon is beaten for the Dog, the Lord for the Servant, he humbled himſelf and took our nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to ſanctifie, nay to glorifie our Nature, in which nature he ſuffered, for this onely end, to make us accepted; <hi>Ideo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Dei factus eſt homo, ut homines faceret filios Dei, Therefore was the Son of God made the ſon of Man, that the Sons of Men might be made the ſons of God.</hi> Behold then and admire what love the Father hath ſhewed unto us, that we ſhould be thus made and called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cauſe the Formal cauſe.</note> But to proceed in order: I will begin with the firſt cauſe of our Regeneration: The formal cauſe; God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Progenuit Deus,</hi> God begets us: And the word the Apoſtle uſeth here to <hi>beget</hi> is worth your ſerious obſervation: it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>peperit,</hi> a word which the Learned give to the ſoul as well as unto the body, to the ſpirit as well as to the fleſh of man: For we muſt underſtand that the ſoul and ſpirit of man hath its birth and children, as well as the fleſh and body:</p>
            <p>As for example: Memory that is the birth of the Braine, thoughts they are the birth of the Heart, and Grace that is the child of the Spirit; I, and there are dolours and pangs, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and ſorrows, throbs and throws, gripes and convulſions in this our ſecond Birth, as many (if not more) and as great (nay greater) than in our firſt. <note place="margin">Note.</note> The mourning weed, the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting eye, the pale countenance, the voice of lamentation, the broken heart, the contrite ſpirit: <hi>Mary Magdalen's</hi> tears, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem's</hi> ſighs and groans, who wept continually in the night, with <hi>David,</hi> who waſhed his bed, and watered his couch with his tears; <hi>Jacob's</hi> wreſtling; <hi>Paul's</hi> combat, and complaint, <hi>Miſerable man that I am, who,</hi> &amp;c. (It being as painfull for a man to be delivered of his ſinne as ever it was for a poor, wracked mother to bee delivered of her burden) that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being laid upon our Spiritual conception, which was upon our Natural, <hi>I will greatly multiply the ſorrows of thy conception, in labour, and ſorrow,</hi> &amp;c. All theſe doth the Lord cauſe, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43024:12"/> raiſe in a man before this new man can be conceived in him, or born of him. When the eyes are red with tears, and the heart doth ake with groans, when the ſoul and body like the Virgin <hi>Marie's</hi> is ready to be divided as with a ſword: when with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> we roar and cry for the very diſquietneſs of our hearts; with <hi>Rebecca</hi> feeling the old man and the new, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhe did <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſtrugling in her womb, we cry out, <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> when with the woman in the <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. we cry out, and are pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ready to be delivered; the great red Dragon ſtriving to hinder our converſion, as he did her conception; Then, then doth this New man begin to conceive and quickend: For as no birth of the creature can be without ſorrow, and pain, No death without dolour, no inciſion, or cutting of the fleſh without ſharp, bitter, or grievous dolours: So cannot the heart be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, our regeneration or new birth effected without much grief and anguiſh of ſpirit. You know that the Babe that hath lien but nine moneths in the Mothers womb cannot be born without ſharp pain, &amp; doth any Chriſtian think to be rid of his ſin, in which he was conceived and born, which alſo hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and bred in him, and which he hath nouriſhed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered many years in his bowels, without great dolor and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows? No, no, but as <hi>Pharoah</hi> then burdened, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſoareſt when they were near their deliverance out of his bondage: And as the dumb Devil then vexed and tore the young man moſt, when our Saviour was ready to caſt him out; So Sathan alwaies troubles the Godly moſt unceſſantly and grievouſly when their deliverance from his bondage is nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: and as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hath greateſt wrath becauſe he knows his time is but ſhort.</hi> Which doctrinal Obſervation hath a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may comfort the dear children of God when they feel ſuch inward pains and dolours, and aſſure them they are but the ſanctified troubles of conſcience, and the pangs of their New Birth; and therefore not to faint or be diſcouraged though they feel them in a plentifull manner: And if man never feele theſe ſorrows, nor are acquainted with this bitterneſs of ſpirit, with this contrite heart, with theſe wreſtlings and fightings: If the New man and Old, the Fleſh and Spirit never make a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43024:12"/> nor are together by the ears in the members; If they find not <hi>the law of the members rebelling againſt the law of the mind</hi> (for they be theſe inward Civil Wars which make the beſt Reformation) ſurely the Enemy poſſeſſes all, all being in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace alwayes, and ſuch may fear they are not yet in the ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fortier eſt qui ſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And though feares and faintings, diffidences and doubtings, theſe inward terrours and ſorrows be found and felt in a plentifull manner, the heart is not to bee caſt down, nor the ſpirit to be diſquieted (although diſquieted) for as I ſaid, theſe pains and pinchings, and contractions of heart, are but the pangs and throws of the New Birth, theſe tears, and <hi>gemitus columbini,</hi> Dove-like chatterings are ſure evidences of a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall conception: for Sathans cloſeſt, and hotteſt, and fierceſt ſiege is ever laid to the Caſtle of the moſt rich and precious ſoules.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly; It is a note of Inſtruction to ſuch as think the worke of their converſion to bee an eaſie work, or ſuch a work as may be effected with peace and pleaſure (whereas that ſin that was contracted with peace and pleaſure muſt ever be diſſolved with pain) Converſion is called the difficult work of Faith, and the duty of Chriſtianity, a working out of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling (and fear hath pain) a very hard and difficult work it is; For there muſt be a cutting off the right hand, and a pulling out the right eye, caſting away thoſe ſins and pleaſures which are moſt dear and near unto us. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re muſt be leaving and forſaking Father and Mother, Wife and Children, Brethren and Siſters, Lands and Livings, renoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing all deareſt, and neareſt relations, abandoning all cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes which have been pleaſurable and profitable to us, and cleaving cloſe to Chriſt and his Faith and Truth; according to <hi>St. Hieroms</hi> ſtout and Chriſtian reſolution; If my Mother that bare mee hung about my neck weeping and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling if my Brethren ſtood about me beſeeching me to continue in my wicked courſe of life, I would caſt my Mother to the ground, I would tread and trample upon my brethren to ſerve my Lord and Maſter; I would leave and contemn all to enjoy him; <hi>For he that loveth Father and Mother more than me is not worthy of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly, it is a note of confutation and reproof to them who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43024:13"/> think they can by their own power and ſtrength induce or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline their hearts to grace and goodneſs; We cannot reform our ſelves: Indeed eaſily enough (God knows) we did, and do deform our ſelves, but none but God can reform us: It is Gods onely proper and peculiar work to regenerate and reform<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By him we are renewed into our firſt image. Non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can change the heart but he that made the heart; none but the hand that made us can mend us. It is Gods work, and it is marvellous in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, or ſhould be ſo. It is he that brings to the birth, and gives ſtrength to bring forth: For, <hi>Shall I cauſe others to bear,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and my ſelf remain barren? No, I will pour out my spirit upon all fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is God that worketh in us to will and to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his good pleaſure:</hi> It is he that doth create in us new hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and renews right ſpirits within us, <hi>Dabo illis cor novum,</hi> I will give them a new heart and ſpirit, and cauſe them to walk in my ſtatutes. It is not in the power of man to adde one cubit to his ſpiritual ſtature, to make a hair white which is black: Far leſs can he change his heart to make that clean which is foul, holy which is unholy, and naturally the ſink of ſin and all uncleanneſs. It is from God we become his Sonnes: He ſends his ſpirit into our hearts, <hi>his ſpirit of Adoption whereby we cry Abba Father, Rom.</hi> 8. 15. But Adoption is where there is no g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niture or beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that doth <hi>filium facer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> not <hi>gign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> It makes a ſon, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets none, it is not after likeneſs but liking; it is not of nativity but nuncupation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Adoption, that is Gods acceptation of ſons: Generation is the impreſſion of the Image God in thoſe ſons adopted. Now Generation is twofold, according to Nature, and according to Grace: According to Nature, and ſo Chriſt alone is the natural begotten Son of God: According to Grace, and ſo every man is his ſon: Obedience to Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, conformity to his will be apparent Teſtimonies of our Sonſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p. <hi>To as many as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his word to them he giveth power to be the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From that that hath been ſpoken ariſe two general propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be ſpoken of out of the firſt cauſe of Regeneration.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a new Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niture and Birth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That God himſelf is the author and cauſe of this Birth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43024:13"/>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a new Geniture and birth: Whoſoever is in Chriſt, is a new, or another creature.</p>
            <p>Poets feign of <hi>Baccbus,</hi> that he was the ſon of <hi>Semele,</hi> and the ſon of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> of <hi>Semele</hi> an earthly Woman, and of <hi>Jupiter</hi> a God. And <hi>Plautus</hi> writes of <hi>Hercules,</hi> that he was the ſon of <hi>Amphitruo,</hi> and ſo mortal; and the ſon of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and ſo immortal: What was but feigned in them, is true in us. In every Regenerate man, there are two men:</p>
            <p>The firſt is from the earth, earthly, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, and ſo he may ſay <hi>to corruption, thou art my father, and to the worm, thou art my ſiſter and mother.</hi> The ſecond is from heaven, and ſo he may call God Father, and hath full inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and power to call Chriſt his elder brother: <hi>Being the firſt born amongſt many brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In our firſt birth we are born men by the will of men; In our ſecond birth we are begotten Chriſtians by the will of God.</p>
            <p>In our firſt birth our mortal fathers beget us to ſucceed them; we are born to die: In our ſecond our immortal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther begets us to live and abide with him forever.</p>
            <p>In our firſt birth our Fathers muſt die before we the ſons can inherit. In our ſecond the children muſt die before they can obtain their heavenly Fathers Inheritance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In our firſt birth we are conceived and born in ſin, and ſo by nature are children of wrath. In our ſecond we are the workmanſhip of God, created in Chriſt to good works, and ſo conſequently the heirs of grace and glory: In a word, a double Pedigree is in every Saint, one of mortality, another of eternity. <hi>Cum peccatorem dico duo dico,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> when I ſpeak of ſinner, I mean two men, a ſinner and a Saint, a man, and a Chriſtian man: One born after the fleſh, called the old man, another after the ſpirit, called the new.</p>
            <p>From which Doctrine ariſe three conſiderations, or obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The verity and truth of our new birth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The ſimilitudes and likeneſſes between our firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43024:14"/>
                  <item>3. <hi>The eminency and dignity of a Chriſtians new birth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The verity and truth of our new birth: We are as truly ſaid to be <hi>renati,</hi> as <hi>nati,</hi> born again, as born at all. For if the wicked be <hi>damna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i antequam nati,</hi> damned before they be born; is it a harder thing, being once born, to be born again? Surely in ſenſe and reaſon it is harder farr to make ſomething of nothing, then to make that better which was ſomething. It is as eaſie to mend as to make, eſpecially when God is the workman; elſe it is a great deal eaſier to mar then to make or mend: <hi>Difficilius eſt ſtruere quam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruere.</hi> I know (as I ſaid before) that this unto fleſh and bloud ſeems very ſtrange, becauſe the natural mans faith goes not beyond his eye: But (as a Father well notes) If in the ſecond reſurrection (the raiſing of the body out of the grave) God can reſtore that which was conſumed to nothing, and make it a more perfect and ſound body then ever it was. Surely in the firſt reſurrection from ſin to grace, he can renew and reform that body and ſoul which he firſt made and inſpired, and he that firſt created them, can renew and amend them.</p>
            <p>Strange it ſeems to the eye of reaſon, but conſider the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and the wonder will ceaſe: <hi>Ille ſuſcitabit te qui creavit te,</hi> ſaith the Father; <hi>Ille reformabit qui formavit te,</hi> ſay I, <hi>ille reficiet te qui fecit te:</hi> he that formed thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will reform thee; he that made thee will mend thee: Reaſon ſees not this. But <hi>ubi ratio deſinit, fides incipit,</hi> where reaſon ends, faith begins, and therefore <hi>crede quod non vides, &amp; videbis quod non credes;</hi> Believe what you ſee not, and you ſhall one day ſee what you would not believe. But is there no Sun, becauſe he that wants his ſight ſees it not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is there no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation or new birth, becauſe the carnal man wants faith, which is the ſouls eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by which it is diſcerned. <hi>Stephen</hi> when he was going to be ſtoned, he ſaw Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of his Father (which none of his perſecutors could do) In like manner the regenerate man (even in his moſt heavy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and at the point of death he) ſees how God is his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43024:14"/> which the natural man cannot ſee, becauſe it is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſcerned.</p>
            <p>But ſince the knowledg of regeneration is ſo needfull, and the work ſo ſecret and myſtical, how may any Chriſtian know that he is regenerate, and what are the trueſt ſignes and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences thereof? For the firſt who require and requeſt to be inſtructed and taught in this ſaving doctrine; and which the Diſciples demand what is the meaning of this Parable? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Firſt by defining, ſecondly by ſhewing the evidences and infallible ſignes and tokens of it. Regeneration then is this; It is the change of the whole man from one thing to another, the change of the body and ſoul from ſin to ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, from darkneſſe to light, from the power of Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 18. It is a Sanctifying throughout, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Now the very God of peace, &amp;c.</hi> But not any waies to confound Regeneration with Sanctification (for that may be a miſtake) Regeneration is defined by the Learned to be this, It is an act or work of Gods wonderfull power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the elect by the Miniſtry of the word (through the operation of the ſpirit of God) that of children of wrath by the deſert of ſin, we are by grace made the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God; or more briefly, It is a grace of God whereby the corruption of nature in believers is daily renewed to the image of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d; it is I ſay again, a grace of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Who according to his abundant grace hath begotten us to a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope,</hi> by which (corruption of nature (for that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per object of it, called in Scripture the old man, or fleſh) is renewed <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>which is a word of religion oppoſed to the old cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption drawn from the old <hi>Adam</hi> (for ſo is the new birth by the ſpirit oppoſed to the old birth by the fleſh, <hi>John</hi> 3.) to the image of God, ſee <hi>Phil</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            <p>Again, the word (renewed) importeth a compleat work upon the whole ſubject; for as in the birth of a child, not one part, or more parts and members, but the whole child is born; ſo is this new birth, the whole man is born again; as we are ſanctified (and as <hi>David</hi> praies to be purged and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) ſo we are regenerate throughout, the whole man muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43024:15"/> be a new creature (for whoſoever is in Chriſt is ſo) which is not the framing of ſomething out of ſomething, but of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of nothing. And I pray you conſider, that as in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mutation and change, one thing removes, and another ſucceeds. So in this generation or new birth, one thing comes in the room of another; and in this birth from above, one thing dies which is corrupt nanture, which muſt die, or we muſt die (if we kill not the ſin in us, the ſin in us will kill us.) (This is called the old man) that which is changed, renewed, and quickened, is the new man, and therefore whoſoever is in Chriſt will put off the old man which is corrupt through deceiveable luſts, and will put on the new, which after Chriſt is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe True holineſſe, note the word, for there is great emphaſis in the word true, and a great deal of feign'd and falſe holineſſe in the world. The Axiom of the Polititian being too much in requeſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio ad morem non ad rem attinet.</hi> True religion is for the manners, not for the main, tis ſomething for his credit, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his profit, <hi>Machiavels</hi> leſſon is learned over and over, the ſhew of goodneſs and vertue is profitable and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but the uſe and practice a trouble, it doth <hi>aggravare ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam,</hi> burden the ſoul, and hinder mens projects too much. Beloved, it will ask a long time, and much labour in many, to unlearn thoſe two Leſſons. But this let me tell them who live by them, <hi>Dediſcere quod malum eſt, eſt doctrina optimo.</hi> To unlearn what is evil, is the beſt learning; and without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Piety is the beſt Policy; or as a King once ſaid, Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is the beſt Policy; and as <hi>David,</hi> though a man after Gods own heart, ſaith that the beſt wiſdom is to be wiſe to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The fear of God is the beginning of wiſdom, a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding have they that do thereafter. A man never begins to be intelligent untill he begins to be obedient, and the beſt plot is to ſave a ſoul, to loſe which, he that knew the price of ſouls well tels us, the gain or purchaſe of the whole world cannot recompence; he that to gain the whole world would loſe his ſoul, makes but an unwiſe bargain; which bargain was wiſe enough, were not the pooreſt deſpiſed ſoul of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43024:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> value, the regenerate and true Chriſtian knows the value and worth of his ſoul and therefore deſires to be renewed in the ſpirit of his mind, and he deſires to know what the good and acceptable mind or will of God is.</p>
            <p>And indeed in the mind, or ſpirit of the mind, the work of regeneration is firſt wrought; as God in the creation began firſt with the light, <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> Let there be light: ſo in our new creation he begins with illumination, he firſt ſtrikes up one light into the mind, and they that were once darkneſſe, are now light in the Lord Chriſt Jeſus, ſpeaking to the mind and underſtanding, as he did once to the blind man in the Goſpel, <hi>Ephatha,</hi> be opened, and this new created light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly baniſheth all the darkneſſe of the mind and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (blinded before by the god of the world) as the riſing of the Sun diſpels all foggs and miſts, and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in another place, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>He preſently puts off the old man with his deeds, and puts on the new man, which is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in knowledge after the image of God: Oportet enim eum qui alteram vitam incepturus eſt pecori fineas imponere:</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves him who is beginning a new life, to put an end to the old.</p>
            <p>And give me leave I pray you a little ſeriouſly and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſiſt upon this Point, this ſaving Point.</p>
            <p>Conceive I pray you that to be regenerate and new born, to be a new creature, or as my Text ſaith, the firſt fruits of Gods creatures, is not to become new in ſubſtance, but in qualities, and doth not conſiſt in multiplying bodies by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but in changing of ſouls or minds into a new form: For <hi>non naſcimur, ſed naſcimur Chriſtiani nec tam generatio quam regeneratio ſpectanda eſt:</hi> We are not born, but we are made Chriſtians; neither is generation ſo much regarded as regeneration, becauſe in our new or ſecond birth we are not made the ſons of man, but the ſons of God.</p>
            <p>As when the ſpirit of magnanimity and valour, and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government came upon <hi>Saul,</hi> it carved him into a new man.</p>
            <p>So when the ſpirit of ſanctification and holineſſe deſcends
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43024:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> upon any, it quite changes and turns them into new creatures, it makes them, as we ſay, new men, and they will anſwer their former ſins and pleaſures, their wanton and vain Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lahs, with whom they have formerly ſpent too much of their precious time, as that young Convert anſwered his enticing and tempting Mrs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſolliciting him to their wonted folly, <hi>Ego non ſum ego,</hi> I am not I, I am not what I was, I was not what I am; he was changed in his mind, or his mind was changed in him. They will reſolve with St. <hi>Peters</hi> converts, The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of our time, or the time paſt of our lives, is enough to have ſpent, or rather miſſpent after the luſts of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, we will ſpend the reſt of our time to the honour and glory of him that died for us. Beloved Chriſtians, thus is a man in his regeneration converted and changed quite and clean in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another man, as Chriſt when he gave ſight to the blind man in the Goſpel, he made him no new eyes, but gave ſight and light to them he had, and as when he raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> and the widows ſon, one out of his grave, another going to it, he created no new bodies, but put life and ſpirit into the ſad.</p>
            <p>So in our regeneration and new birth, God makes us no new ſouls or bodies, but renews, reforms, amends, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them we have. He takes not the eyes out of our heads, but the vanity, luſt, and ſin of the eyes, moving us inwardly to make a covenant with our eyes, not to look upon any tempting object, and we will pray earneſtly with <hi>David, Turn away mine eyes leſt they behold vanity;</hi> and indeed <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> might well pray to God to turn away, open, or amend his eyes, for both were naught<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>One was bloudſhot with the murther of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had <hi>Bathſheba</hi> the Pearl in it; and indeed <hi>occuli ſunt in amore duces,</hi> as in love, ſo in luſt, the eyes are as leaders or windows to let ſin into the ſoul, <hi>Eve</hi> ſaw the beauty of the fruit before ſhe luſted after it, and <hi>Achan</hi> the wedg of gold, and the Babyloniſh garment before he c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veted it.</p>
            <p>Not our ears but the pravity and ſin of our ears, the deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dulneſſe thereof; and to ſay truth, the firſt ſenſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43024:16"/> ſanctified in our regeneration, is the ſenſe of hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the firſt that was corrupted; our firſt parents by hearkning and liſtning what the Serpent ſaid, were brought into a love and liking of ſin, and a regenerate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian by hearing what the ſpirit ſaith, is brought into an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and deteſtation of ſin: Theſe are the ſenſes of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and knowledge, therefore of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> grace: God opens our ears before he opens our eyes, if we will not hear God, we ſhall never ſee him: The ear is the principal ſenſe ſanctified to receive ſpiritual and ſaving inſtructions, as you may read in the <hi>Proverbs;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes it an impoſſible thing to believe, if we will not hear: The ſpeech of <hi>Lactantius</hi> is worth the noting and quoting too, <hi>Plus eſt in auribus quam in oculis ſitum quoniam doctrina &amp; ſapientia percipi auribus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis poteſt occulis ſolis non poteſt.</hi> The Lord begins his Sermons to his people, <hi>Hear ô Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 6. and upon the condition of hearing and hearkning, all bleſſings are promiſed, <hi>If thou wilt hearken unto my Commandments, all theſe benefits or bleſſings ſhall overtake thee.</hi> And when God had ſent his Son (whom he promiſed long before to ſend) the great Doctor and Preacher of his Church. All the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and receit of him all the reverence and reſpect called for, is but audience, <hi>ipſum audite:</hi> Hear him, Hear my beloved ſons, and it will make you ſons dearly beloved, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hear then and your ſouls ſhall live. If the Prophet ſhould bid thee do ſome great matter, ſaies</hi> Naamans <hi>ſervant to his Maſter, wouldeſt thou not do it to be cleanſed of thy Leproſie, muchleſs when he bids thee but waſh and be clean</hi> (when he went away in a puff and ſnuf (as too many do from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving word) So if God ſhould command us (and we his poor Miniſters beſeech you in his name) to do ſome greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then wee do, would you not do them to ſave your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſouls? muchleſſe would we hear and be happy, Hear and our ſouls ſhall live; hear him here, whom we deſire to ſee hereafter. Beloved, <hi>auditus eſt gradus ad viſum:</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is a degree to ſeeing; if we will not hear God, we ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43024:17"/> never ſee him; and therefore as <hi>John</hi> the Divine exhorts like a Divine, ſo do I, but in his words, <hi>He that hath an ear let him hear, and he that will not hear what the Church, ſaith, let him be anathema, accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, <hi>omnis habent aures audiendi pauci, obediendi:</hi> All have ears to hear with, but few to obey with, ears of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with <hi>Samuel, Speak Lord, for thy ſervant heareth;</hi> or like <hi>David, I will hear what the Lord will ſay unto me;</hi> or with <hi>Mary,</hi> who ſate at Chriſt's feet to hear his Preaching, or like the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles, Hark, it is the voice of well-beloved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee in my Text, what an honour and dignity God hath put upon his word, to beget us to himſelf; of his own will he begets us with the word of truth; and ſhall not we willingly give it the hearing? The Apoſtle in the next verſe makes the only uſe and application of the Doctrin and leſſon here taught. Since the word of truth is the ſeed of our new birth, therefore let every man be ſwift to hear, of a tractable, docible, and meek ſpirit, ready to wait upon God in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and to receive with meekneſſe the ingra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fed word, which being ſo received, is able to ſave the ſoul, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
            <p>Again, God takes not the tongue out of our heads, but he takes away the ſin and iniquity of the tongue (within a man unregenerate, is a world of wickedneſſe (as St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith) The world is not fuller of wickedneſſe, than the tongue of ſin, if unreformed; he takes away therefore in our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and puls out the venom and ſting, and violence of the tongue (which is indeed a ſmall member, but doth great miſchief, blaſphemies, oaths, railings, revilings, curſes, imprecations, lies, perjuries, diſſimulation, all corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, filthy and froathy ſpeeches, which are not once to be named amongſt Saints.</p>
            <p>And as the holy Ghoſt when he came down upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, they ſpake with new tongues (as the ſpirit gave them utterance) So whom the holy ſpirit ſanctifies and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, it gives a new and another language, and though it gives them no new tongues, yet it gives the tongues they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43024:17"/> have a new dialect, their tongues are touched with a coal from Gods Altar, neither have the gift given them of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, and ſpeaking well of their neighbour: As the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſon will not liſten to falſe tales, or tale-bearers, which are <hi>flabellum Diaboli &amp; flagellum juſti,</hi> the Devils Bellows, and the Saints ſcourges (for the tongue kils more then the ſword, the ſword of the mouth, more then the mouth of the ſword) as he will not receive a falſe report a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his neighbour (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, and makes one of the ten notes of a righteous man, of a Citizen of heaven;) So he will not raſhly nor haſtily judge him before he know him, or hear him ſpeak, knowing that he that carries a falſe report, and he that receives and believes it, the one carries the Devil in his tongue, the other in his ears: And therefore they which are born from above, will ſet a watch before their mouthes, and guide the dore of their lips, as the Kingly Prophet ſaith, <hi>They will take heed to their waies that they offend not in their tongue,</hi> and they will utterly purpoſe that their mouth ſhall not offend. They will therefore open their mouthes with wiſdom, and guide their words with diſcretion, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of the good houſe-wife, as ſhe will keep her ſelf, ſo ſhe will keep her words at home within her own dores: The tongue indeed hath a double hedge, teeth and lips, to ſhew it ſhould not eaſily or commonly ſtraggle or wander, or run over. The law of grace, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will be in the lips of the righteous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his mouth will ſhew forth Gods praiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis worth noting, that <hi>David will take heed to his waies, that he offend not in his tongue;</hi> intimating, that the ſafety and ſecurity of a mans waies of his whole life and converſation conſiſts much in the government of his tongue: <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> facile violat, quae facile volat,</hi> as eaſily ſins as moves, and it moves often too eaſily, no arrow or bullet out of a gun, or bow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wounds more ſpeedily or quickly, or pierceth more deeply or deadly, then a tongue primed with the powder, and ſet on fire with the fire of hell. And therefore <hi>James</hi> tels us, that he is a perfect man (that is) in a great part regenerate, that can rule it; for it is the opinion of a Father, That half the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43024:18"/> ſins committed in the world, are committed through the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe and unrulines of the tongue. <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tidiana for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nax is humana lingua,</hi> The tongue of evil men is a continual Fornace wherein the names of righteous men are tryed. And therefore to end this point, The government of the tongue is an infallible note and evidence of ſome progreſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in grace: But a regenerate heart, and a wicked tongue, a ſanctified heart, and a virulent, venomous, blaſphemous tongue, never go together: For if the ſpring or fountain the heart, be clear and pure, needs muſt the ſtreams be ſo; for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaks. When <hi>Socrates</hi> would know the diſpoſition and condition of one that came to be his Schollar, he bid him ſpeak that all might know him: <hi>Sermo virum indicat,</hi> the ſpeech ſhews the man, it is <hi>animi index,</hi> the interpreter of the mind.</p>
            <p>We may eaſily know what is in the heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by that which comes out of the mouth: He is of <hi>Galilee,</hi> ſaith the girl of <hi>Peter,</hi> for his ſpeech bewrayeth him: A man is eaſily diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his language what Countreyman he is, of <hi>Canaan,</hi> or <hi>Aſhdod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly beloved, a ſtinking and ſtrong breath doth not more evidently declare ill lungs, and corrupt inwards, then evil language an evil liver; Mettals are known by their tinkling and ſound, and men by their tunes, and tongues, by their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</p>
            <p>This is very certain, Gods children have alwaies Godly language, and their ſpeeches and words are ſeaſoned with wiſdom as with ſalt, as St<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith (For wiſdome ſeaſons our actions; as ſalt doth our meat) their words ever tend to edification, to the building up their brethren in the faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In a word, in the work of regeneration, God takes not the heart out of our bodies, but he takes corruption out of our hearts: He heals by his ſpirit and grace, that deadly and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned fountain, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> by his handfull of ſalt cured the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome waters of <hi>Jericho:</hi> And indeed their ſanctification and regeneration begin ever: As Nature in forming, ſo grace
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43024:18"/> in reforming begins at the heart, and makes a through change there; as when the Adulterer and Fornicator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes chaſte, and conſiders that his body is, or ought to be, the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, and therefore not be made a ſtable for <hi>Bacchus,</hi> or a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew for <hi>Venus,</hi> but to be preſerved in purity, in holineſs, and honour, and not in the luſt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſence, as the heathen which knew not God, abſtaining from all appearance of evil, not entertaining luſt into his heart by any inordinate deſires, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 26. Nor into his eye by wanton and laſcivious looks (for you ſhall read in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 14. of eyes full of Adultery, or the Adulterers) nor into the tongue by filthy and rotten ſpeech, nor by any means into the act by committing that great wickedneſs, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> cals it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. and therefore will daily ſweeten and perfume this Temple of God with the incenſe of prayer and ſupplication, watering it often with the unfeigned tears of contrition and ſorrow with <hi>David</hi> (that devout penetent) who made his bed to ſwim, and watered his couch with his tears, and ſweeping it with the beſome of repentance, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no foule corner or ſpiders web within the heart or houſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When he conſiders, that in other ſins a man may <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care,</hi> and <hi>perire ſolus,</hi> ſin and periſh alone, but in this ſin of uncleanneſs, he carries company to hell with him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the arms and lips of a harlot are like the Iron I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, which cruſhed the curſt ſacrifice to pieces; or like the Ivy which embracing the Tree, kil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in theſe ſins, he ſins, firſt againſt God the Father who created him in holineſs and righteouſneſs, and in that manner to ſerve him. Secondly, againſt Chriſt the ſonne which redeemed him by the ineſtimable price of his moſt precious bloud, and to this end he redeemed him that he might glorifie him in his ſoul and body, who had redeemed both. 3. That it is againſt the ſpirit of Chriſt, which is a pure and clean ſpirit; and none but the pure in heart ſhall ſee God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That it is againſt our reaſonable ſervice of God, for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43024:19"/> in all reaſon we ſhould make them the members of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which are thus redeemed, and give up our ſelves, ſouls and bodies, a living ſacrifice unto God, which is our reaſonable ſervice of him, glorifie him both in our ſouls and bodies, which hath redeemed both.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it is againſt our Covenant in our baptiſm, and againſt our calling, for having as the Apoſtle ſaith, ſuch precious promiſes, as to be called the ſons and daughters of God, we ſhould cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. laſt <hi>c.</hi> 1. and perfect holineſs in the fear of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, that it is againſt a mans own body, which no other ſins are, and gives a deep ſtain and blemiſh, not only to his own name, but to the name of his ſeed: and that they that do ſuch things ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of God. But the fire of luſt ſhall have the fire of hell, and the ſins of uncleanneſs, ſhall be puniſhed in <hi>Gehinom,</hi> a place of unbelievers: Secondly when the glutton and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſon puts a knife to his throat, as <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth, moderateneſſe, and reſtraining his appetite in full provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, remembring even that moderate precept of St. <hi>Paul, Whether ye eat or drink, or whatſoever elſe ye do, do all to the glory of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 31.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the drunkard becoms civil and ſober, walking ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly as in the day, not in ſurfetting or drunkenneſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting them dear pleaſures which we repent on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and remembring that ſaying of the Poet, If the pains and aking, and grief of the head came before drinking, as they come after, no man would be drunk. If the Rhumes, Catarhs, Apoplexes, Dropſies, and infinite other Diſeaſes, the natural offspring of that unnatural ſin were conſidered, no man would exceed.</p>
            <p n="4">Fourthly, When the covetous and worldly man, who made his money his God, and gain his godlineſs, the tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and griping miſer is become mercifull and liberal, and of a lover of the world, a lover of God and his word, and concludes that godlineſſe is the beſt gain, having the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43024:19"/> of this life, and of that which is to come, and truſts to that word of truth, <hi>primum quaerite, regnum coeli,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caetera aut aderunt aut non oberunt,</hi> other things ſhall not be wanting, or if they be, the want of them ſhall not hurt us: For if we have not wealth, the riches of the world, we ſhall have contentation and patience, the riches of the mind: For he is not rich that hath much, but he that is contented with that he hath.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the envious and malicious man is become loving and charitable, conſidering that God is love, and the more loving any man is, the liker God; that envy and malice are the very characters of the Devil (you are of your Father the Devil, ſaith Chriſts to the envious Jews) for his works ye do.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When the angry, froward, and wrathfull man is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come meek and patient, poſſeſſing his ſoul in patience, in the midſt of the greateſt troubles, knowing that by faith we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs Chriſt, by love, our brethren, but by patience our ſelves, that anger reſteth and abideth in the boſome of fools, and ſuffers not therefore the ſun to go down in his wrath, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering that he which ſleepeth in anger or malice, hath the devil for his bedfellow; is therefore ſlow to anger and wrath, conſidering well that the wrath of man doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the righteouſneſs of God, <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When the proud man is become lowly and humble, knowing that God reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble; that the meek ſhall poſſeſs the earth, and the humble God will teach his waies, that they are they ſhall find reſt to their ſouls. That pride caſt the Angels out of heaven, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> out of Paradice, the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> out of his name and nature, and therefore cannot bring any man to heaven; for humility goes before honour; but pride goes before a fall: <hi>Humilitas claritatis meritum, cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas humilitatis praemium:</hi> Humility is the deſert of glory, glory the reward of humility: <hi>ſi vis capere celſitudinem Dei prius cape humilitatem Dei.</hi> In a word, when every ſin
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43024:20"/> doth return as he is commanded from his evil way, doth ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do good, when in a holy anger and indignation that they have been the ſervants of ſinn ſo long; they caſt off their old Livery of ſin, as blind <hi>Barte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus</hi> caſt off his old Cloak, and with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> ſmite upon their thigh, asking and enquiring, what have we done, wretch as I am, I am in way to be undone? when he ſmites upon his breaſt with the Publican (his breaſt the ark and cheſt of all iniquity) and in faith and feeling cries out, Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to me a ſinner, when weary of his ſinfull courſe, he doth reſolve with the prodigal, to leave it and return home to his Fathers, with words of unfeigned ſorrow and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will go to my Father, a happy thing we have a Father to go to, and ſuch a father, <hi>tampater nemo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When with <hi>Eliphas</hi> in <hi>Job,</hi> a man ſeriouſly reſolves, and reſolvedly purpoſes, If I have done wickedly, I will do no more (which was the caveat Chriſt gave to them he healed) conſidering that <hi>Inanis eſt paenitentia quam ſequens culpa co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inquinat,</hi> That true repentance is not only a repentance for ſin, but a repentance from ſin, as the Apoſtle cals it, <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from dead works,</hi> then is this great work wrought, this man is a new creature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To aſſure our ſelves that we are regenerate and born of God, obſerve farther, that as <hi>Elizabeth, John</hi> the Baptiſts mother did aſſure herſelf that ſhe was with childe, when ſhe felt the babe to leap and ſpring in her womb.</p>
            <p>So when we find our wils conformable to Gods will, when it is our meat and drink to do our heavenly Fathers will, when we are ready to anſwer to the call of every heavenly motion, as the eccho to the voice of man, and anſwer with <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, Speak Lord, thy ſervant heareth.</hi> With <hi>David, It is written I ſhould do thy will, I am content to do it, O my God, thy Law is in my heart.</hi> When the word of God is to us as it was to him, our longing and our love, this is a ſure evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our new birth; for where there is a new birth, there will be a new life; where there is a ſpiritual and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly birth, there will be a ſpiritual and heavenly life, if we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43024:20"/> be born of God, we will with <hi>Enoch</hi> walk with God, and will be followers of God as dear children. The natural child, they ſay, lives not untill forty five daies after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception be expired; but the regenerate and new-born Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian begins to live aſſoon as he is conceived, there will no longer be a life led after the will of the fleſh, or of our own luſts, but after the will of God, and the will of God is our holineſs.</p>
            <p>He that is born from above, will reſolve to ſpend the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his ſhort time to the honour of him that died for him, and it will appear whoſe heeis by a life led in holineſs and righteouſneſs, in faith and a good conſcience, he will walk worthy of the calling whereunto he is called, and will ſay with <hi>David</hi> when he was moved to ſome unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and uncivil action: Is it nothing to be ſon in Law to a King? If we be the ſons of God, our carriage and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be according; <hi>Our light will ſo ſhine before men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 14:</p>
            <p>God begets to holineſs and righteouſneſs, and by this heavenly generation we are made partakers of the Divine nature, having eſcaped the corruption which is in the world through luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, We are the offspring of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the life led after our converſion, is called the life of God, to which the unregenerate are ſtrangers. And it is called the life of Chriſt too; now that is after my converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I live no longer, but Chriſt liveth in me, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. He that is Gods ſon, will do Gods work, and the work of God is conſtant and univerſal obedience.</p>
            <p>A ſecond note and evidence of our regeneration is, a through change and reformation of heart and life. The new man is of a renew'd mind, old things will be caſt away, and all things will become new, he will cleanſe himſelf from all wickedneſs of fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As firſt, there will be a new light ſtruck up into the mind and underſtanding, they will be illuminated to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43024:21"/> the things which be of God (which the natural man cannot do) as the further obduration or occecation, and banding of a man is the note and ſigne of a reprobate, when the God of the world blinds the eyes, as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>So it is an evident note of one begotten of God, of one born from above, when he is renewed in knowledg and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and knows the mind of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly there will be a new quality in the will, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to hearken to the voice of Chriſt in all things, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, <hi>He that is born of God, heareth Gods word,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, there will be a new converſation in the life, and this holy converſation will be manifeſted by the fruits and effects of the ſpirit, love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, meekneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> characters and ſtamps of holineſs, ſtill led in the practice of any reigning ſin, after the luſts of the fleſh, is a manifeſt note of a carnal man; but he that is born of God ſins not, as you ſhall hear anon; ſin is in him, but it reignes not in him; <hi>Ineſt,</hi> but <hi>non praeeſt</hi> or <hi>obeſt,</hi> it is in him, but not over him, nor doth he obey it in the luſt and power thereof; he ſins indeed, but yet not he, but the ſin that is in him. In his mind he ſerves the law of God, though in his fleſh the law of ſin; it is againſt his heart and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his will and purpoſe. Again, he liveth not, nor lieth in any known ſin, but his courſe and indeavour is after the Commandment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There will be new affections, as the love of God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all ſin, for it is not enough to leave ſin, but to loath it and hate it; as <hi>Ammon</hi> (when he had ſatisfied his luſt upon his ſiſter <hi>Thamar</hi>) it is ſaid, <hi>He hated her afterward more then ever he loved her.</hi> Thus will Gods child deal with ſin, and deſire to purifie himſelf, as God is pure, caſt off his ſin as a menſtruous cloth, and ſay, Get thee hence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There will be conſtant and holy means uſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and improve all theſe graces, to keep alive this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is the ſpirit of prayer and ſupplication the bellows of the Sanctuary.) The child of God will ſpeak the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43024:21"/> of God. Prayer is the Saints language on earth, as praiſe is in heaven. An infant is no ſooner born into the world, but preſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it cries after the breaſt for the mothers milk (that which doth not, is ſtill born, or a dead child) So a man is no ſooner born of God, but he will deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that he may grow thereby. It is the note of a wicked man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of one dead in ſins and treſpaſſes (that he cals not upon God) that is, caſts off the fear and worſhip of God. If ſome were tryed by this rule, it would appear of what breed and birth they are, they are of <hi>Babels</hi> breed, and therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (above all) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their milk (this word from the people) which withdraw theſe two Paps of the two Teſtaments (which are as the dugs to nouriſh Gods children) or gives them this milk mingled with their own traditions (pretend and boaſt as ſhe will) is but a ſtrumpet and ſtep-mother, and not the true ſpouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So much of the verity and truth of our new birth, and of the evidences and ſignes thereof.</p>
            <p>Come we now to ſimilitudes and likeneſſes between our firſt and ſecond birth, which are many, but I will reduce them to ſeven.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In our firſt birth there is <hi>mutatio à non ente ad ens,</hi> a change from a no being into a being. Thus it is in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth; there is a change from a no being in grace, to a being in grace; new ſeeds of grace are ſown in the heart, where before they were not, and the man which was dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, is now quickned; <hi>mutat quod erat &amp; incipit eſſe quod non erat.</hi> It changes what it was, and begins to be what before it was not. I know the Papiſts alleadg this ſaying of the Father to prove and uphold their I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ol of Tran<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſubſtantiation, but the Father uſeth it to prove the manner and truth of our regeneration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In our firſt birth there is many times the ſimilitude and likeneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the form and favour of the parents (of them that do beget) this alwaies holds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true in our ſecond birth (in our birth from above) God begets no ſon or daughter, but he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43024:22"/> begets them after his own Image and likeneſs, as we read <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 3. That <hi>Adam</hi> begat <hi>Seth</hi> after his own image and likeneſs, that is, ſinfull and corrupt, and mortal as he was, and needs muſt be, for that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh. So whoſoever are begotten of God, whoſoever are his off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring and image, his ſons and daughters, are as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, made partakers of the Divine nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. or as <hi>Paul,</hi> We are the offspring of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 28, 29. Foraſmuch then as we are the offspring of God, That which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orn of the ſpirit is ſpirit; but herein ſtands the difference between heavenly and earthly generation, between the natural and ſpiritual birth between the adoption of God and man; man in adopting man to be his ſon, may beſtow upon him his lands and goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but he cannot communicate to him his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or goodneſs; but Gods adoption hath not only in it an approbation and acceptation for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, but he inſtamps up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them his own nature and image, he makes them (as I ſaid) partakers of the divine nature. They are mercifull as their heavenly Father is mercifull, holy as he is holy; holy ſo, not ſo holy, mercifull, and holy according to the manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not the meaſure of Gods holineſs, or mercy, according to the quality, not the equality; perfect as their heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect, in aim, intent, purpoſe, indeavours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; they pray and petition with <hi>David, O that my waies were made ſo direct that I might keep thy ſtatutes.</hi> They preſs hard towards the mark of their high calling, they ſerve God truely and ſincerely, though weakly and infirmly; and what is wanting in the perfection of their obedience, is made up in the truth and ſincerity of it. Neither will God ſee weakneſs where he ſees truth in the inward affections, where the heart is right and good, the obedience thereof is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and mercifully accepted, for God looks at, and cals for the heart, <hi>My ſon, give me thy heart,</hi> Give it me, who firſt gave it thee, give me thine, who gave thee mine nay, the blood of my heart, <hi>Non minus tuum quia meum,</hi> It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs thine if it be mine; nay it cannot be thine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, except it be mine perfectly; for as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43024:22"/> this is all that God requires of his people, only to fear the Lord, and to ſerve him with all their heart, 1 <hi>Jam.</hi> 12. 24.</p>
            <p>Again, they that are Gods ſons are loving as God is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, God is love, and the more loving any man is, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker God, the liker their Father which is in heaven; they are loving and peaceable that are born of God, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, and peacetakers; and S. <hi>John</hi> gives it as granted, that whoſoever loves not his brother, is not born of God, for God is the God of love and peace; <note place="margin">Note.</note> the multitude and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of believers are of one heart and of one mind. They queſtion their ſaintſhip and ſonſhip, who are enemies to love and peace.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore for application of this point, for it needs cloſe application, in theſe divided times, take St. <hi>Pauls</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, <hi>Be followers of God as dear children, and walk in love Eph.</hi> 5. 1, 2. Love is the Chriſtians walk, not his talk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gods children, as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, love not ſo much in word and in tongue (which is moſt of the love in theſe daies, a little warm breath) as indeed and in truth. Let us follow him in theſe pathes of love and mercy, and truth, and holineſs; and though we cannot go his path, let us go as faſt as we can, Let us run the race that is ſet before us, and if we cannot run, goe, if not goe, creep, follow God though it be but ſlowly, and eaſily, though it be with limping and halting, as <hi>Peter</hi> followed Chriſt along afarr off, and as <hi>Aſcanius</hi> his father <hi>Aeneas, Non paſſibus aequis,</hi> with no equal paces. If we cannot write after our copy, yet let us look to it and upon it, endeavour our beſt, and God will accept the will for the deed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Applic.</note> A Note of Doctrine to be taken of in this hatefull and hating age, wherein iniquity abounds, and the love of many (as Chriſt the truth propheſied) is grown cold, ſo cold that it cannot be felt. Brothers at diſſention (as if they were no brethren) Chriſtians without love and charity (as if they were no Chriſtians.) It would make the heart of a righteous <hi>Lot</hi> to lament and bleed, when there wants no more inſtance than what <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to <hi>Nathanael, veni &amp; vide,</hi> come and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43024:23"/> ſee. Love is the badge and cognizance of Gods children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>By this ye are known to be my Diſciples, if &amp;c.</hi> It is the Chriſtians Cloak and Livery, therefore the Apoſtle bids us put on love. This Cloak will cover many ſins, it is both <hi>indumentum</hi> and <hi>ornamentum,</hi> not only a cloak to cover and hide, but an ornament to adorn; it was wont in times paſt to be the comprimiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and determiner of all Law-ſuits; <hi>Let not us fall out, for we are brethren,</hi> ſaies <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot,</hi> the greater to the leſſer: What brethren and fall out? No, it is a good and joyfull thing for brethren to dwell together in unity. It was the harlot would have the child divided, the true mother would have it live: they ſhew of what houſe they came, of what diſcent they are who love to live in envy and malice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in hatred and diviſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you are of your father the devil, ſaith Chriſt to the envio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jews, for his works ye do; profeſs wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y all, they have not God for their Father, nor the Church of God for their Mother, nor Chriſt for their Saviour who are enemies to peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for as I ſaid, True belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> are of one heart, and of one mind, of one ſoul. Give me leave to give you a ſtrong, patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and effectual motive to love and peace, the character of Gods children. God is the God of peace, Chriſt Jeſus is the Prince of peace, the holy Ghoſt is the Spirit of peace, the Goſpel is the Goſpel of peace, your calling in general is a calling of peace ye are called to peace: Ours who are the poor deſpiſed Miniſters of Chriſt, is a calling and commiſſion of peace; and we are commanded, nay charged, into what houſe ſoever we come, to preach and pray for peace to that houſe (how well and faithfully ſome have done their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, let the world judge.)</p>
            <p>When Chriſt came into the world he brought it; there was peace over all the world, the Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> was ſhut, and wars were ceaſed at every gate, and the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of heaven ſang at his birth and nativity, <hi>Glory be to God on high, on earth peace, good will towards men</hi> (and therefore ſurely there is heavenly muſick in it) <hi>David</hi> ſaith, God will give unto his people the bleſſing of peace: So that peace is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43024:23"/> a bleſſing; nay the bleſſing of bleſſings, the ſugar and ſweetning of all bleſſings; for nothing is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing without it; what are our ſweeteſt comforts, our deareſt and neareſt relations, our riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, magnificence, or any worldly accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if not enjoyed in peace? It was therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in <hi>Eſay,</hi> That when Chriſt ſhould be born (Chriſt the Prince of Peace) the peacemaker, that men ſhould break their Swords into Ploughſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-Hooks; that is, there ſhould be unity and peace in the world, all animoſities and hoſtilities ſhould be laid aſide (and ſo they are where Chriſt is born in us.) Nay even the Souldier with a ſword in one hand, and fire in the other, he cries and ſpeaks aloud, <hi>Sic quaerimus pacem.</hi> Thus we look for and ſeek for peace, peace being the end of war; when Chriſt lived in the world he taught it, <hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with another. And if a man ſmite thee upon one cheek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if he take away thy Cloak; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When Chriſt went out of the world he made peace, his Legacy, <hi>Peace I give you, my peace I leave unto you;</hi> and when he roſe again, he made it his ſalutation: He came in unto them, the dores being ſhut, and ſaid, <hi>Peace be unto you;</hi> and when he had ſo ſpoken, he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide, as if he had ſaid, ſee here, my dear friends, how dear your peace coſt me (even theſe wounds in my hands and ſide) <hi>ne rumpatis eam,</hi> break not that ſo eaſily which coſt me ſo dear, upon every poor and ſlight occaſion, or for the love of every baſe ſin or pleaſure, make
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43024:24"/> not me to bleed again: Enough I think to coole the fiery ſpirits.</p>
            <p>If this will not ſerve to take the ſting of envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice out of the minds of many, but ſtill like Salamanders they will live in the fire and heat of contention, I will ſend ſuch down to the place of utter confuſion, for an argument of peace, and they ſhall hear even the Devil himſelf pleading hard for that which he continually breaks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 30. <hi>What have we to do with thee, Jeſus, thou Son of God, art thou come to torment or trouble us before the time?</hi> They that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all the world, you ſee, would not be troubled themſelves. Enough to cool the fiery ſpirits of ſuch as make diviſion their muſick, and love to fiſh in troubled waters, nay that fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t trouble the waters themſelvs, and then complain of the Lamb that comes to drink of them; let me ſend ſuch to meditate upon that ſpeech of Chriſt, That <hi>Belzebub is not divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Belzebub, if he were, his kingdom could not ſtand;</hi> That ſeven devils agreed in <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> a legion in another; whereas with grief be it ſpoken, three ſcarce agree with us in a Family, or ten in a Pariſh. But were our State and Commonwealth as ſtrong as the kingdom of Satan, diviſion and contention (if continued) muſt needs bring it to deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ruine.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Joſeph</hi> therefore when he ſent his brethren home to their father, gave them this godly advice, <hi>Fall not out by the way,</hi> the ſame I exhort and beſeech in the bowels of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed peace-maker (looking all towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> let not <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> have our hearts) let us go on in love and peace, and the God of love and peace will be with us: O let not diviſion of hearts hinder the building of Chriſtianity, as diviſion of tongues hindred the building of <hi>Babel. Filia diſſentionis deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio,</hi> The daughter of diſſention is diſſolution, yea and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The factions and diviſions between <hi>Simeon, Eleazar,</hi> and <hi>Jehochanon,</hi> foretold and propheſied by Chriſt, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully recorded by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a fellow-ſufferer and eye-witneſs, laid the Temple and City, and the houſes of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and not one ſtone upon another. The Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43024:24"/> you know (who was a Prince of peace, and type of Chriſt) was built in peace, there was not the ſound of an Axe, Hammer, or any other inſtrument heard in the erecting of it: Indeed it was beaten down with Axes and Hammers (as <hi>David</hi> dolefully complains) but it was ſet up without them. The myſtical and ſpiritual ſenſe you eaſily apprehend. The ſpiritual Temple and houſe of God in us, is, or ſhould be built in peace and unity, without clamor, ſtirr, or noiſe, we ſhould, as the Apoſtle ſaith, edifie one another in love and peace: for <hi>Si collidimur frangimur,</hi> If we be broken and unbound, we are undone, ſignified by <hi>Scelurus</hi> faggot, a known ſtory, <hi>Diviſum eſt c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum jam jam interibunt,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. Their accord is gone, their cord is untwiſted, they cannot ſtand, <hi>Iſcouedo</hi> the Spaniſh Poet, being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his Maſter, <hi>Philip</hi> the third, by what means he might become Maſter of the Low Countries, he gives him this ſhrewd and ſubtile councel, Divide them amongſt themſelves, according to <hi>Machiavels</hi> precept to his <hi>Caeſar Borgia, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide &amp; impera,</hi> make a diviſion and get the Dominion. It is obſerved by many learned men (and lame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed by more) that the unkind and needleſs diviſion of Chriſtian Princes amongſt themſelves, have added more Lands and Territories, more Dominions and Principalities unto the Turks Empire, then their own Sword and Bow, As <hi>Phrahartes,</hi> one of <hi>Pompey's</hi> chief Captains ſaid of <hi>Julius Ceſar's</hi> Conqueſts, <hi>Noſtra ruina factus eſt magnus,</hi> By our ruine he is raiſed and made great, his gain hath been our loſs, his riſe our downfall; our breaches and diviſions (which like <hi>Reubens</hi>) have cauſed great grief of heart, have been his utmoſt advantage: Whilſt we wory and fight, and ſheath our ſwords in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bowels; they ſay with the Edomites, There, there, ſo would we have it: they ſing and laugh with <hi>Nero</hi> (having ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire) When I am dead, let all the earth burn: And therefore (for concluſion of this point) in which I have been ſomething earneſt and long (being very ſeaſonable and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preſs in the condition we are in) let us but adviſedly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43024:25"/> and ſoberly conſider the many miſchiefs which factions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions have brought into the world, and cloſely lay them to heart, and it cannot but warm us with that heavenly fire of love (the image of our Father) and account it with <hi>David</hi> (who though a fortunate and valiant Warrier, yet a man of peace, nay altogether for peace) a man much vers'd in battel, and ſing it with him, It is a good and joyfull (or a pleaſant and joyfull thing) for brethren to dwell together in unity: For our own particular, let the men of our famous Nation give me leave to ſpeak to them, and put them in mind of their own ſtrength and honour, in intimating unto them the memorable words and obſervations of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, the Champion of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Monſieur <hi>Roan,</hi> the Champion and Marſhal of <hi>France,</hi> in the beginning of the Reigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed memory, walking in his Gallery with <hi>Roan,</hi> and being in ſerious diſcourſe of the unity of the Queen with her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, of their unanimity and ſtrength, of the wealth and ſtrong ſcituation of the Iſland (which he ſaid was impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unacceſſible, being walled with a Wall of Braſſe) (he meant invironed and compaſſed with Seas) <hi>Roan</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered like a prudent obſerver, <hi>Angle le terra grand animal.</hi> The Land of <hi>England</hi> is a ſtrong and mighty body, which can never die except it kill it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And ſurely they deſerve more then one death, who willingly and deſperately goe about to be their own murthers, with <hi>Nero,</hi> to kill, and rip up the bowels of their own Mother.</p>
            <p>And to me it ſeems a myſtery (indeed the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is in it) that many have, and will have order in their own houſes, and it is the Item and injunction they give to their ſervants, (when they hire them) this is the order of my houſe, and thus and thus you muſt doe and obey; and yet would have none in the great Houſe (the Church and Commonwealth) neither Magiſtrate nor Miniſter. I will ſay no more to ſuch, than the great Apoſtle hath ſpoke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43024:25"/> me, If any man be contentious, we have no ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, nor the Church of Chriſt, and that God is the God of order, not of confuſion: And how can he ſerve God that is the God of love and peace, without peace and love: His Name is love, and his Law is love.</p>
            <p>And therefore to conclude this Character of a Chriſtian, and ſtrongly (once more) to move to unity and peace. Take three pathetical and emphatical motives and perſwaſions from the Doctor of the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Now I beſeech yor brethren, by the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (by which you are named or called) that you all ſpeak the ſame things, and that there be no diviſions amongſt you, but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and the ſame judgement.</hi> Love and unity are the Cement and Glew of Chriſtianity and Religion, the unity of the ſpirit is beſt kept in the bond of peace.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, any comfort of love, any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, any bowels of mercy, fulfill my joy, and be ye like minded hrving the ſame love, being of one mind, and of one accord, and let nothing be done in ſtrife or contention</hi> (for that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does all) God came to <hi>Adam</hi> in the cool of the day, and to <hi>Elias,</hi> not in the thunder, or fire, or ſtorm, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt (but in the quiet ſound) 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 19. 11. And it is worth your noting upon what perſons, and at what time the holy Ghoſt came down, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 1, 2. <hi>He came down upon the Apoſtles whilſt they were all in ſupplication and prayer, and</hi> (of one mind) <hi>in an upper Chamber in</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of unity deſcends upon none, but upon ſuch as have unity of ſpirit. Beloved, if ever we find an enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſpirit, or feel the deſcent of ſpiritual bleſſings in an ample and plentifull manner, we ſhall find it to be when we are in unity and unanimity: And therefore if we will have a ſenſible apprehenſion of the ſpirits communion and benediction, let us (in the name of God) meet in one Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43024:26"/> in the ſame mind of thoſe primitive Chriſtians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to which we pretend did, and be in the ſame poſture and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion they were, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 31. <hi>Who being of one heart, and of one mind,</hi> the place moved where they met: When we hold one of <hi>Paul,</hi> another of <hi>Apollo,</hi> another of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> are we not divided? and divided prayers are fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (when the River is divided into many ſtreams and currents, it cannot carry our Veſſels) our hearts wanting love and unity, and our Altar fire, the incenſe of our prayers cannot aſcend.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Note that place well, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11. <hi>Finally my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren farewell: be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you;</hi> and if God be with us, and for us, we need not care who can be againſt us: God is the God of love and peace, and the Godly are peaceable, and loving. By thoſe characters, men ſhew their heavenly birth, their birth from God, whoſe name is Love, and whoſe Law is Love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In our firſt birth, <hi>Generatio unius eſt corruptio alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> the generation and begetting of one, is the death and corruption of another: untill the old man be dead, the new man cannot quicken, As it was propheſied of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> when they were in their mothers womb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the elder ſhould ſerve the younger: So untill the elder man be brought into ſubjection to the younger, there can be no peace in the members, neither is this work wrought.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In our firſt, ſome are more eaſily conceived and brought forth into the world, ſome with much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty and pain, with greater ſorrows and anguiſh, with many throbs and throws, crying and roaring, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pained with the woman in the twelth of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ready to be delivered.) Thus it is in our ſecond birth, ſome are more eaſily converted and turned to God, as the Jews at <hi>Peters</hi> firſt Sermon; and <hi>Lydia</hi> and the Gaoler at <hi>Pauls. Acts</hi> 16. Some coſt their ſpiritual Parents a great deal more pain and labour, as the Galathians <hi>Paul,</hi> My little
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43024:26"/> children, cryes he, of whom I travel in childbed again untill Chriſt be framed in you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 19. and the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> conſidering and grieving at the obſtinacy and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of Gods people, cries out, <hi>Ah my belly, my belly, how am I pained?</hi> which complaint ſignified nothing elſe but the extream ſorrow and heart-breaking which the Prophet ſuffered, to reduce and bring the diſobedient Jews into the Fold of Chriſt, to regenerate and convert them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In our firſt birth there commonly goes an eſpouſage and contract before the marriage, to make the iſſue and act legitimate and lawfull: So Chriſt, to make himſelf a lawfull ſeed, marries himſelf firſt unto the Church; <hi>Conglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinabo,</hi> or <hi>deſponſabo te mihi fide,</hi> I will marry thee, unto me in faith; faith is as it were the marriage-ring (and that is the reaſon I think after the covenant and contract, that the Ring was given in marriage.) Now being thus married unto Chriſt, we are no more two, but one fleſh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 24. and never did any man hate his own fleſh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 29.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In our firſt birth we grow and are framed in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe by degrees: firſt the heart (for that is <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum vivens</hi>) then the brain, then other arteries and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, untill we come to be a perfect and entire birth: Thus it is in our ſecond birth (as Nature in forming, ſo grace in reforming, begins at the heart) that is firſt reformed, and renewed, and then all the parts of the body, and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoul, will be amended and reformed: <hi>David</hi> therefore (though polluted and defiled throughout, yet he praies for the ſanctifying and purging of no part but his heart. <hi>Create in me, &amp;c.</hi> Purge my heart, and I am clean all over. As therefore <hi>Jehu</hi> ſaid, in his travel, to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab</hi> (when he met him in the way) <hi>eſt ubi cor rectum,</hi> is thy heart right as mine is? The ſame in effect God ſpeaks in truth, <hi>eſt vobis cor novum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is your heart good, is it renewed? Then come up into my Chariot, come ye bleſſed children of my Father, &amp;c. For the new heavens, nor the new name (the name of Filiation and Sonſhip) are for none but new creatures.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43024:27"/>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, in our firſt birth we are born babes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot men. It were a monſtrous thing to ſee a new borne child at his full grouth the firſt day or week: Thus it is in our ſecond birth, we are born babes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not men: Babes, and need the ſincere milk of the word; and then come to be ſtronger men by degeees, and to have need of ſtronger meat: <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo naſcitur artifex,</hi> No man is his Craftſmaſter the firſt day. This I note, againſt the ſudden grouth of many, who boaſt of their ſoon acquired grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and think they are at the height of religion, before they know the foundation, or have learned the Principles: There were ſteps and ſtaires to <hi>Solomons</hi> Throne, and ſo there are to Gods, to heaven: No man can ſtep thither at one ſtride; we come to heaven <hi>per gradum, non per ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> by degrees, not by leaps. How comes it to paſſe then that many think they are at the higheſt pitch of grace, when they have ſcarce made one motion or ſtep towards it.</p>
            <p>Certainly many that are ſuch Saints on a ſudden, that think they are ſo high above others, are carried up, or rather hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by their own fancy and imagination: For neither holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nor heaven are got, but by gradual and orderly walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Gods Statutes being a way, continually leading to ſome glorious end.</p>
            <p>There is an orderly going up the ſtarrs in <hi>Jacobs</hi> Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a leiſurely going forward by degrees, a daily profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and proceeding in grace and goodneſſe, as the young babe growes daily and hourly towards his full pitch and grouth, ſee 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 2., 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Adde to your faith vertue, to your vertue knowledge, to your knowledge temperance, to your temperance pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, to your patience godlineſſe, to your godlineſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe, to your brotherly kindneſſe love Sudden growthes are ever ſuſpicious: Remember <hi>Jonas</hi>'s gourd; what came up in a night, withered in a day: Come but a little perſecution for righteouſneſſe lake, and this forward ſeed is ſcorched, this haſty corn is blaſted, they have no root,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43024:27"/> as our Saviour ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. or as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> They are not rooted in knowledge, nor well principled, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can never come to perfection: As <hi>Iſaac</hi> therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of <hi>Jacob</hi> in another ſenſe, <hi>How is it you found it ſo quickly my ſon? Gen.</hi> 28. 20. So may I ſay of theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ones, which like young lapwings run into the world with the ſhell on their heads; how is it you found grace ſo quickly, that you are ſo good, and heavenly ſo ſuddenly, that you know more in a day, than your Teachers in all theirs. Heaven is a penny, and it muſt be wrought for; he muſt endure the heat of the day, that will have the wages at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening: It is a Pearl that muſt be digged for, he muſt ſweat and take pains that will find it; it is a Garland that muſt be run for, a Crown that muſt be fought for: it muſt be got <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi> not <hi>ſapore,</hi> by ſweat, not by ſloath, <hi>ſuperantibus dabitur:</hi> To them, and none but to them that overcome ſhall this Crowne of life be given: Be thou conſtant, or faithfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, and <hi>&amp;c.</hi> None but conquerors over ſin and Satan, ſhall ever wear this Crown. And this fight is not eaſie or ſhort, we muſt reſiſt unto bloud: There is the Law of ſin in the members rebelling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianity (as I told you) is called the difficult work of faith, and a working out our ſalvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: It is no eaſie thing to believe; but ſo hard, that when the Son of man comes he ſhall hardly find faith upon earth.</p>
            <p>From this that hath been ſpoken, an uſefull Doctrine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it ſelf; Namely, That there muſt be a grouth in grace; a proceeding and going forward in holyneſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: For children and babes grow in ſtature as they doe in years; ſo muſt Chriſtians. It were a wonder, nay a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle almoſt (for any) to ſee a young child born to day, at the ſame growth and pitch ſeven years hence: And very lamentable I am ſure it is to ſee many aged men, and men well ſtricken in years, going out of the world before they knew why they came in: to die before they knew how to live to ſee <hi>elementarium ſem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> an old man in his A. B. C.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43024:28"/> young, old men: Gray before they are good (as we ſay) a man well gone in years, not at all improved in grace. The Prophet <hi>Eſaiah</hi> ſpeaks in his time of children of an 100. years old, 65. 20. We may apply his Prophecy to our times; And <hi>Seneca,</hi> that divine Heathen tels us, That it is a ſhame for a man, an old man, who to ſhew he hath lived long in the world, hath no other witneſſe to produce but his gray hairs. And <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cynick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as bitterly as wittily, told one that boaſted of his age and elderſhip (and therefore ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be reproved) that he had put off <hi>pueritiam,</hi> but not <hi>puerilitatem,</hi> he had put off his childhood, but his childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he had not put off. Beloved, though we ſhould be as new born babes (in deſire to the ſincere milk of the word) yet we ſhould not alwaies be as babes new born, ſtand at a ſtay like a horſe in a Mil, which is all the day going about, and yet at night in the ſame place he was. If we proceed not, nor make any progreſſe in grace and goodneſſe, we have no grace nor goodneſſe at all; like Scullers, or Oars, if we goe not forward, we goe backward Examin we then the truth of our ſpiritual birth, by this of our natural (I mean by this likeneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imilitude to our natural) Art thou a ſtronger man in Chriſt now then formerly, this day then yeſterday? are thy ſins more mortified and weakned, and thy graces more ſtrengthened? is it between thy old man and new, the fleſh and ſpirit, as it was between the houſe of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Saul?</hi> Doth <hi>Davids</hi> houſe grow ſtronger and ſtronger, <hi>Sauls</hi> weaker and weaker? Doth the old man die daily, and the new grow and quicken? Try and ſift thy heart and the graces thereof by this rule, for <hi>minime ſane eſt bonus, qui melior eſſe non vult:</hi> good that man or woman cannot be, which endeavours not every day to be better: <hi>Si dixeris ſufficit periiſti:</hi> if thou ever ſay thou art good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, thou art in a manner undone; for in the waies of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and goodneſſe not to goe forward, is to goe backward: Grace and goodneſſe never were in us, if they are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in us, as I ſaid; He was never good at all that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired not every day to be better. And therefore though we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43024:28"/> be never a day good as we ſhould be, yet let us be every day better then we were; every day break one thread of that net in which we are enſnared, every day grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the ſecond of <hi>Peter,</hi> the 3. and laſt: For howſoever we ſhall not find it profitable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor it may be commendable, in theſe evil daies (wherein grace and goodneſſe is aſhamed of it ſelf, and the name) yet I am ſure we ſhall find it comfortable: <hi>Indice nos ſentire meliores,</hi> every day to find our ſelves better and better. For faith and a good conſcience, a regenerate and holy life, had it no further or future reward, it is it ſelf <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium ſui,</hi> its own reward, and gives ſuch unſpeakable peace and quietneſſe to the ſoul and mind, that none know it but they that have it. It was the commendation of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. That as he grew in years, he grew in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God and man; and it will be our exceeding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſee, that our laſt daies be our beſt daies, and that our latter end be better then our beginning. They that are planted in Gods houſe ſaith <hi>David,</hi> are flouriſhing and well liking, and will bring forth moſt fruit in their age. Yea and even thenw hen their Almond Tree doth flouriſh, their hearts will be (as neare as they can) as white in innocency, as their hairs are with age; and indeed herein is our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified, if we <hi>&amp;c. Jo.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 8. As the little child, then grows in every member of the body, ſo the regenerate growes in every affection, in every grace: for graces and goodneſſe (like the babes milk) are ſo ſweet to the ſouls of them that taſte it, that they do, they muſt needs long for more.</p>
            <p>As Then the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when ſhe heard Chriſt ſpeak of a water of which whoſoever drank, ſhould never thirſt more, cries out, Lord give me evermore of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And the Diſciples hearing Chriſt ſpeak of a bread of which whoſoever did eat, ſhould never hunger more, deſire, Lord give us evermore of this bread. So whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth once taſte how good and gracious the Lord is (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks) muſt needs pant after him as the hart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:43024:29"/> and as a new born babe deſires the ſincere milk of the word, that he may grow thereby: for no growth, no grace.</p>
            <p>So much of the ſimilitudes and likeneſſes betweene our firſt and ſecond birth. Follows now the eminency and dignity of a Chriſtian new born, and truely very ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and great is the dignity and honour of a Chriſtian born of God; as the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſaid of the quondam Senators of <hi>Rome, Quod vidi Senatores, tot vidi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:</hi> So many Senators as I ſaw, I ſaw ſo many King.</p>
            <p>The ſame, and more, we may ſay of them that are born of God, <hi>Quot vidimus in terris renatos, vedebimus in coelis reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes:</hi> So many as we ſee on earth converted, we ſhall ſee in heaven crowned. See a little into this dignity.</p>
            <p>He that is born from above hath God for his Father, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is from above, to wit, the Church for his Mother, Chriſt Jeſus the ſon of Gods love for his Brother; the Noble bloud of Jeſus Chriſt runs in the veins of every true Chriſtian: He is of the bloud-Royal. For as I told you before, they are by this heavenly birth, made partakers of the Divine Nature, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. and ſo a noble generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a royal Prieſthood, a peculiar people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the nobleſt born of any in the world, are they that are born from above. It was the religious and pious ſpeech of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Rome, Mallem eſſe membrum Chriſti quam caput im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii,</hi> I had rather be a member of Chriſt then Head of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. And <hi>Luther</hi> to that purpoſe, <hi>Mallem eſſe Chriſtianum ruſticum, quam paganum Imperatorem:</hi> I had rather be a Chriſtian clown, then a Pagan King. Rejoyce not (ſaith Chriſt) in theſe and theſe things, that you have preached in my name, and in my name have caſt out devils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in this rejoce, that your names, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So boaſt not ſo much that you are born of theſe and theſe houſes, of that high and noble bloud, as that you are born from above. Look not ſo much to your natural generation, as to your ſpiritual regeneration, <hi>Civis aequat omnes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares naſcimur, &amp;c</hi> The duſt equals all. Look therefore to that birth by which we are made heirs of God, and joynt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43024:29"/> heirs with Chriſt. The true honour (I ſay again) is to be born again; by which birth we are allied to Chriſt, and made of his alliance and linage: For he that doth the will of my Father (which is in heaven, ſaith Chriſt) the ſame is my ſiſter and brother, and mother; and when ſome came and told him that his mother and brother were without to ſpeak with him; he anſwers (as I told you) <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. and <hi>Luke</hi> 8. by pointing to his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 49, 50. He ſtretched forth his hands towards his Diſciples, and ſaid, Behold my mother and my brethren; for whoſoever doth, &amp;c. The ſame <hi>Luke</hi> 8. My mother and my brethren are they that hear the word and do it, <hi>verſes</hi> 21. By which places of Scripture we ſee plainly and evidently, that Chriſts reſpects are greater, and he is dearer and nearer to them that are united<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to him by faith, than by bloud, by ſpiritual regeneration, than by natural generation. And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> from hence is bold to affirm, <hi>Felicior Maria credendo in Chriſtum quam concipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndo carnem Chriſti: Mary</hi> was more happy in believing in her Son, than in bearing him, in believing in him in her mind, than in bearing him in her womb. They are dearer and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Chriſt, that are allied to him by faith, than by the fleſh: and this our Saviour mildly intimated to the woman, who looking too carnally and ſenſually upon his outward and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural generation; and crying out, bleſſed the womb; and he corrects her in theſe words, <hi>Nay more bleſſed are they that hear the word of God and do it.</hi> It is not the conception of the body, but the conception of the mind, which unites us to Chriſt; for howſoever by the body we are born at firſt, by the mind we are born again: The womb, of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception lies higher, namely in the heart, where the ſeed of the word is ſown to receiv the ingraffed word, and to conceive the new man, and by faith to impregnate and bring him forth. This is the work of regeneration, and this unites us to Chriſt, makes us bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh. The word of God (which is called the ſeed of our new birth) goes in at our ears, from thence down to our hearts, and there (as I ſaid) it doth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pregnate and fructifie, and bring forth the new
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43024:30"/> Men. God begets us of his will by the word of truth. I will conclude this Point with the Prayer of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one of his Sermons, beſeeching God that <hi>Quicquid meditatum eſt cor meum:</hi> whatſoever my heart hath profitably meditated upon this divine Subject, may enter (from my mouth into your ears, from your ears into your hearts, from your hearts ſpring forth in your lives and be fruitfull; ſo that receiving the ingrafted word with meekneſs, it may be able to ſave your ſouls.</p>
            <p>As you have in part ſeen the eminency and dignity of a Chriſtian (of which you ſhall hear more anon) ſo I pray you note three great and ſingular priviledges and prorogatives of one born of God; they are worth your noting and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Firſt, <hi>They that are born of God, ſin not,</hi> 1. <hi>John.</hi> 3. 9. He that is born of God, doth not commit ſin: Sin not (may ſome ſay) how can you make that good? ſince the moſt righteous ſin ſeven times a day; and there lives not a man upon earth that ſins not? If we ſay we have no ſin, ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> We, I for one, we are not only deceivers, but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. In many things we offend all (ſaith <hi>James,</hi> We, he puts himſelf in, <hi>James,</hi> called the Juſt) puts himſelf into the number of ſinners (We offend all) all of us in many things, and many of us in all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verebar omnia opera mea,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> I feared all my works, knowing that in the beſt of them is weakneſs, in the worſt, wickedneſs, error in all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> cries out, Who knows how often he offendeth? (The higheſt form of believers are not without the actings of ſin, though the loweſt forms are not under the dominion of ſin) And what were <hi>Noahs</hi> drunkeneſſes, <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt, <hi>Abrahams</hi> diſſimulation, <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery, <hi>Solomons</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Peters</hi> Apoſtacy, <hi>Thomas</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>credulity, were not theſe ſins? <hi>Noah</hi> was a juſt man in his generation, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull, and friend of God; <hi>David</hi> was a man after Gods own heart, nay the Father of Chriſt (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh) <hi>Solomon,</hi> a type of Chriſt and Prince of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43024:30"/> Peace. <hi>Peter</hi> the prime Apoſtle, upon whoſe faith Chriſt did build his Church. <hi>Thomas</hi> vouchſafed that never man was to put his finger into the hole of our Saviours ſide, and to handle his wounds; yet theſe tall Cedars were not only ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but overthrown: <hi>Et ſi non timuit lupus illum gregem intrare:</hi> If the Wolfe feared not to enter into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old of which Chriſt was the Shepherd, how may we fear our ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſince theſe ſtrong ones were ever taken with faults, no ſmall ones, and infirmities, not a few: Let him that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth take heed. 'Tis true, <hi>peccatum ineſt in electis, non praeeſt,</hi> It is in them, not over them; <hi>remanet non regnat,</hi> it remains in them, it reignes not in them; <hi>Vivit, non vincit,</hi> it lives in them, but it conquers them not, <hi>bellat,</hi> not <hi>debellat,</hi> it wars, but it wins not. They are not ſo perfect, ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctified here in this life, that ye fail not, or fall at all, nor ſin at all, that <hi>peccatum non ſit,</hi> or <hi>niſit,</hi> that ſin ſhould not be; or be in them; but they are ſo upheld and preſerved by the power of God unto ſalvation; <hi>ut peccatum non praeſit non obſit,</hi> that ſin ſhould not reigne in them, nor ruine them; becauſe (as I ſaid) God keeps the feet of his Saints, and his ſeed, that is, his ſpirit and word remains in them. So that though they fall, yet they fall not foully, or finally, though ſin be in them, yet it reignes not in their mortal bodies, that they ſhould obey it in the luſts and deſires thereof; becauſe they be born of God, and by faith lay hold upon the Lamb of God, which hath taken away, &amp;c. and they have an Advocate with the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we are to know that this Advocate, this Jeſus who was ſo called becauſe he ſhould ſave, though he hath taken away the ſtrength and ſting of ſin, the guilt and condemning power thereof, yet he hath not taken away the being of ſin: The ſite of ſinne, that Chriſt hath not ſtirred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the ſpite and might of it, that he hath quelled; the might that it ſhould not <hi>regnare,</hi> reigne; the ſpite of it that it ſhould not <hi>damnare,</hi> damn: Sin is in the beſt and holieſt, but it condemns not them that are in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 11 They commit no wickedneſſe (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) that walk in thy waies, that is willingly, purpoſely,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43024:31"/> or reſolvedly: They ſin indeed out of weakneſſe and frailty, and error, out of negligence and careleſneſſe, and raſhneſſe, but not out of wickedneſſe, intention, or preſumption, out of infirmity, and inadvertency; they ſin, but not delightfully, or deſperately, willingly, or conſtantly; they ſin not finally, or to death, with their mind they obey the Laws of God, though with their fleſh the Law of ſin: or as one ſaies upon the place, They live not unto ſin, but unto Chriſt who died for ſin; or (which is the trueſt and the moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expoſition of all) They ſin not, becauſe their ſin is not imputed nor laid to their charge. They are looked upon in the face of Gods Anointed, and ſo God ſees no iniquity in <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. Thou art all fair my love, ſaith Chriſt, and there are no ſpots in thee: ſpots ſhe hath, as there be ſpots in the Moon, ſhe hath ſin in act, but her ſins are not imputed: Thou are fair ſaith Chriſt, through the beauty that I have put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. In this ſenſe they that are born of God, ſin not; they have ſin in them, but not ruling or reigning in them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples when he found them aſleep, The ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weak: And the Spouſe of her ſelf and her drowſineſſe, I ſleep, but my heart waketh: So the Saints of God, the beſt have their nods and neves but the heart wakes when the eyes are cloſed; even in their falls and weakneſſes they have a deſire to ſtand and to be ſtrong in the Lord: and as I ſaid, With their mind, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. laſt. They ſin, I ſry again, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not their work or trade; It is not they, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, but ſin that remains in them. Secondly, It is their deſire and intention to do good; 3. They lie not, they continue not in ſin, but their courſe is after the Commandment, and a walking in and by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: whereas the wicked and unregenerate, they ſin purpoſely with delight and pleaſure, and they continue in their ſinne, making it their work end trade; they make it their Plough (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith) They plough iniquity (and therefore they muſt needs reap miſery,) They work it, and cannot ſleep except they commit it; they love it, and live by it; it is not onely their love, but their life: and as it is their trade and their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43024:31"/> work, ſo it is their ſport and paſtime, their mirth and recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, this fool (the ſinner) makes a ſport of ſin: a fool indeed; for have they any underſtanding that work wickedneſs (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) whereas the regenerate man grieves and mourns, and laments for it, his righteous ſoul is vexed at it; and he never finds reſt or quietneſs, untill he feels in his conſcience the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of his pardon in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Book <hi>de civitate Dei,</hi> ſets forth the difference between the ſins of the regenerate and unregenerate, very learnedly and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, by a compariſon and inſtance in <hi>Tarquin</hi> and <hi>Lucrete,</hi> where ſpeaking of her raviſhment by him, he ſaith thus, There were two bodies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet but one Adulterer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>peccatum factum eſt de illa, non ab illa:</hi> ſin was done with reluctancy and ſtriving, and ſtrong oppoſition upon her; it was not done willingly or delightfully by her: The ſame may we ſay concerning the ſins of the regenerate; ſin is done with reluctancy, and ſtriving, and oppoſing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting upon the Godly, it is not done willingly, or purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or readily, or pleaſingly by them: Like men ſpiritually oppreſſed by the potency and power of the enemy, by the ſtrength and power, and violence of Satan, <hi>The good they would do they cannot do it, but the evil, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> which makes them heavily and dolefully to complain, <hi>Miſerable men that we are, who &amp;c.</hi> and concludes the point, having ſhewed the difference between the ſins of the godly and ungodly, in two ſentences, which deſerve your obſervation: 1. <hi>Verus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitens ſemper eſt in timone &amp; dolore;</hi> a true penitent is alwaies in fear and grief. In fear leſt he ſin; 2. In grief for ſinning. Try thy ſelf by this; Art thou afraid when thou goeſt forth into the world (where men walk as amongk ſnares) leſt thou ſin, and be enſnared; and if thou beeſt overtaken with a fault, doſt thou grieve and lament thy folly and weakneſs, and art never at reſt untill thou haſt made thy peace with thy God? It is a certain ſigne of thy ſonſhip, that thou art the child of God: thy ſin ſhall not be imputed. The ſecond obſervable note of the Father there, is this, <hi>Peccata non nocent quae non placent:</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe ſins do never hurt, which do not pleaſe; they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43024:32"/> damn not any man that delight him not, becauſe they be not committed with the heart, mind, or will, for it is a true rule, <hi>Quod cor non facit non fit:</hi> What the heart doth not, is not done. So much of the heart and mind, as is in any ſin, ſo much it is a ſin, where they are not, there is no ſin, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally or evangelically, at leaſt condemnatory: <hi>Theſe things I write unto you,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, that you ſin not,</hi> which is an impoſſible thing in a ſtrict and legal ſenſe, as I have ſaid; but in an evangelical and Goſpel ſenſe, it is poſſible: You muſt not ſin as wicked men do, who do nothing elſe but ſin. (Their life being a continuall and continued courſe of ſinning) who make it their work and trade, work it with both their hands, and all their heart, earneſtly and conſtantly, which they doe not who walk in Gods waies, and who are Gods children; but he that is born of God, doth righteouſly, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 29. And he that is born of God, heareth Gods word, <hi>John</hi> 8. 47. He carrieth a flexible and docible heart unto the word, which is the ſeed of our new birth, and preſerves a man from ſin.</p>
            <p>Carry we our ſelves therefore like holy perſons, like men born from above: and if <hi>David</hi> thought it a great honor to be ſon in-law to a King, Let Chriſtians think it a tranſcendent dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and honor to have God the King of Kings for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall ſuch a man as I fly, ſaith <hi>Neh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miah?</hi> So ſhall ſuch a man as a regenerate man ſin wilfully, or preſumptuouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſuch a Father as God is to him? whoſe eyes are over him to protect him, and his hands under him to ſupport him, who numbers his very hairs, and <hi>ſi ſic curat ſuperflua in quanta ſecuritate eſt anima:</hi> They that are Gods children cannot, will not ſin: they have the bleſſing of impotency and weakneſs in their regenerate part, that they cannot ſin ſtrongly: though they have not that bleſſed liberty in the regenerate part, that they cannot ſin at all. <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> though he was lame in his feet, yet he was of the bloudroyal, ſon to a Prince, and grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to a King ſo may a Chriſtian be the child of God though he be lame and weak in holy duties and performances. He walks uprightly, that walks ſincerely, and with a good heart. And as I ſaid before, God will not ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> where
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43024:32"/> he ſees truth in the inward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffections: It was the happineſſe of <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradice, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuit non peccare:</hi> He could not have ſinned: God gave that power and ſtrength unto the ſoul in the Creation, that he was able to have preſerved himſelf from ſinning: It is our unhappineſs now after his fall: <hi>Non poſſumus non peccare:</hi> We cannot chuſe but ſin, being born in iniquity and conceived in ſin: ſinners from the womb.</p>
            <p>It will be our happineſſe in heaven, <hi>Non poſſumus peccare:</hi> We cannot ſin at all. In a word Not to ſin at all is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and holineſſe of heaven: Not to ſin wilfully or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, is the holineſſe and happineſſe on earth.</p>
            <p>This then conſider and apply, for the concluſion of this comfortable priviledg, That to be preſerved from ſin (from the hurt and danger of ſinne) is a great priviledge and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to uphold thee, &amp;c.</hi> And this bleſſing and priviledg God promiſed, <hi>Job</hi> 5. his faithfull ſervant, and obedient child, That he ſhould not ſin, which is the greateſt comfort the world can afford: It is (if conſidered) the next priviledg to God, and the higheſt priviledg of man, of mortal man: And when in a full ſenſe man ſhall be taken from ſin, he ſhall be received to joy, to fulneſs of joy, and the more we empty of ſin by repentance, the more we are filled with joy, which is found and felt here by the teſtimony of our own conſciences, which is the very beginning of heaven and of happineſſe in this life: The more holy, the more happy. Pray we then to God who is the only cleanſer and purifyer of the heart, our only ſanctifier, and pardoner of ſin: To make us ſo happy here as to be holy (that is, not to have our ſin imputed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For bleſſed is he whoſe iniquity is forgiven, &amp;c.) and ſo holy here, that hereafter we may be eternally happy.</p>
            <p n="2">The ſecond Priviledg.</p>
            <p>He that is born of God, doth overcome the world. It is Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine too, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. The world is too baſe for their high-calling in Chriſt Jeſus: They are born from above, and therefore ſhould not mind things below<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>The world God ſet and placed under mans feet to tread and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43024:33"/> trample upon, not to ſet his heart upon: God made the world for man, and therefore he made man himſelf, for a better thing then the world is, for himſelf and his Kingdom: and therefore the Church of Chriſt, the mother of us all is deſcribed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1. To be clothed with the ſun, and to have the moon under her feet, and upon, &amp;c. the meaning is, ſhe was cloathed with Chriſt the Sun, that is, with Chriſt the Sun of righteouſneſs, according to that ſaying of St <hi>Paul, Put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Indeed he is <hi>indumentum &amp; ornamentum,</hi> our garment and our glory: She had the moon under her feet, that is, ſhe had all earthly and worldly things under her, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the moon for its waxing and waning, changing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, and increaſing, for her continual variations and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, ſhe treads them all under her feet, ſhe makes light of them, knowing that ſhe is born fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m above, and there is her inheritance, ſhe therefore regards not, nor values earthly things in compariſon of heavenly: for he that is cloathed with the ſun, cares not for the light of the moon, which hath all her light from the ſun: So he that hath God, what need he care for the world: he that dwels in the ſun, what need he care for any light from the moon, which is Gods creature, and made only for mans uſe and ſervice: God hath ſet all things under his feet, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Given him rule and authority over all the creatures: He hath given the earth to the ſons of men: It was the obſervation of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit coelumque tueri</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſſit, &amp; erectos, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> Whereas all other creatures were framed with dejected and caſt-down countenances, with faces hanging downwards: he made man with an erect, lofty, and ſtately countenance, that he might by the conſideration of his feature and compoſition, be put in mind of the end of his creation: and as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quae ſurſum ſunt quaerere,</hi> Seek thoſe things which are above: So that theſe Eagles (Chriſtians) ſhould not catch at flyes, nor theſe <hi>Herculeſes,</hi> the offspring of God. Sit at a diſtaff, and do ſuch drudgery and baſe ſervices as the world and fleſh (like <hi>Omphale</hi>) ſhall preſcribe unto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The world I ſay God pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced under mans feet, that his head and heart ſhould not be where his feet troad and trampled.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:43024:33"/>
            <p>Since then the Creatures were all made for Mans uſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, for their encouragement to, and in Gods ſervice, making them all conſtantly and willingly to ſerve Man, that Man might ſo ſerve his Maker with cheerfulneſſe and willingneſſe; Shall Man make himſelfe ſo baſe, ſo diſhonour his high calling, ſo degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as to make himſelfe a ſlave to his ſlave, a ſervant to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with curſed <hi>Cham</hi> whoſe curſe it was to be a ſervant of ſervants: <hi>Amare res ſuas plus quamſe,</hi> to love the Creature more than the Creator, which is bleſſed for ever?</p>
            <p>No marvaile then that God, who is a jealous God, and will not give his honour to another, nor love, affect, or eſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me any thing in the world more than him, or above him, many times drops gall and bitterneſſe into our creature-comforts, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitters our earthly bleſſings, when he ſees us dote too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and place that contentment and ſatisfaction in them, which we ſhould place in him; ſet them in his throne, and make Idols and images of them, falling downe to them, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did to the Calfe, as the covetous man doth to his Gold, calling it his god, and the wedge of gold his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, the amorous and luſtfull man (the <hi>Sampſon</hi> to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe) the proud man to himſelfe and honour.</p>
            <p>Beloved Chriſtians, the next way to loſe any thing is to love it too well; and 'Almighty God when he ſees us ſet too deep an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction and love upon any creature, and prefer any earthly creature in our affections before him, he either takes it quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us, or elſe drops ſome bitterneſſe into it to make it diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtfull.</p>
            <p>Let God therefore have the prime and principall, the ſtrength and conſtancy of our affections, and let us love all other things with a ſubordinate and inferiour love, and all he gives us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, let us love for the givers ſake (as his gifts and bleſſings) and ſo we cannot erre in our love. Let us love other things with a ſubordinate affection to him, and with a willing reſignation of them to his Divine will and pleaſure to his diſpoſall: But the onely meaſure of loving God is to love him without meaſure; we cannot love God too much.</p>
            <p>Secondly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Remember thy ſelf (O Man) whence thou art &amp; the place whither thou aimeſt and tendeſt. Thy face is towards <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:43024:34"/> let not <hi>Babylon</hi> have thy heart. For wilt thou, which art borne for a better inheritance, which ſhalt one day feed of the food of Angels, which ſhalt ſit with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdome of God, wilt thou ſo far diſgrace and debaſe thy ſelfe, thy Father, Friends, and Country, as to ſpend they ſelf and lay out thy ſelf upon earthly and tranſitory things? <hi>Lay out thy labour for that which is not bread, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 55. 2. No, let <hi>Babylon</hi> feed upon theſe diſhes, let the Prodigall eate theſe husks. The teſtimony of Chriſt hath given thee no ſuch legacy, his Kingdome, as himſelf a teſtifies, is not in this world, and ſo conſequently ours, and therefore not our Crowne. Thou art borne from above, therefore ſet not thy affections on things below. They are below thy birth and breeding, thy condition and calling. Set them not therefore above thee, make not thy Servant thy Lord, (the World, and the things therein l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke Fire and Water, are good Servants, but bad Maſters) let them not therefore rule over thee.</p>
            <p>But ſay what we can or will, men will, moſt men ſet their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections upon theſe worldly things, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> (upon good grounds) diſſwades we will faſten our minds upon theſe tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſubſtances, we will ſpend our ſhafts at theſe flying fowles, which have wings like an Eagle, and are vaniſhed as ſoone as poſſeſſed; like little children we will hunt theſe ſhadows, and let reall, ſubſtantiall, and enduring ſubſtances goe. Perſwade we what we can, (had we the tongues of men and Angels) we could never perſwade men from doting upon theſe vaine, tranſitory, deceitfull, and uncertaine riches. But we will build where we cannot ſtay, and anchor where we cannot harbour, and faine would we ſet our reſt here in this reſtleſſe place, this troubleſom and unquiet world, (whoſe whole compoſition is nothing but commotion and tumult) although Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, That <hi>we have no continuing City here,</hi> and the Prophet calls upon us to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and be gone in our affections, for here is not our reſt. And notwithſtanding that urgent precept and counſell of Saint <hi>John, Love not the world, nor the things of the world, If any man, &amp;c.</hi> But his words are but wind, and ſpoken onely to the aire, What not love the world, nor the things of the world? You ſhall as ſoone get the heart out of mens bodies, as the love of the world
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43024:34"/> out of the heart. They are as impatient for riches, as <hi>Rachel</hi> was for a better wealth and ſubſtance, <hi>Give me children or I die:</hi> So give me Riches or I die, (and in deed many die in the too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger purſuit of them, (as ſhe did in her travaile.) God gave her children, but one was her death: So God gave ſome Riches, but it is for their ruine: As God gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> a King in his anger, and took him away in his wrath. Thus though we call God Father, and profeſſe our ſelves his children, yet in our courſes and wayes we ſhew our, ſelves <hi>Terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> filios,</hi> Earth-bred and worldly minded men.</p>
            <p>We ſavour and ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l too much of the earth, our very breath is earthy, and our language and talke of nothing but the world and worldly things. All our labours, talk and diſcourſe tend downwards, and earthwards. We bury our ſelves almoſt alive, and dig and delve like moles and hogs, and ants in the earth; and all for that which cannot profit us or fill us, (except it be with cares and croſſes, with troubles and vexations.) We make our way through thornes, to get nothing but thornes, which pierce us through with many ſorrowes; and many times like ſlippery and falſe friends, forſake us when we have moſt need of them; like Phyſitians, faile us and forſake us at the point of death; or like <hi>Abſoloms</hi> Mule, which ran from him when he had moſt need of him. I dare ſay, many men had been more happy if they had been leſſe great and rich. The greatneſſe and riches of many have been their ruine. The rich travellers life and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney have often been a prey to the cruell and covetous thief.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore thy original, O Man, it is from Heaven; Let thy thoughts therefore be heavenly, thy ſpeeches heavenly, thy converſation heavenly. In all thy earthly buſineſſes, carry a heavenly mind, and when thy hands be upon thy worke, let thy heart be above, where thy Father is, thy Redeemer is, where thy Country<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Friends, and inheritances all are: For as <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove (being out of the Arke) could find no reſt for the ſoale of her foot untill ſhe returned to the Arke againe; ſo the ſoule being come out of heaven from God, can finde no reſt or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent here in this troubleſome world, in this ſea of glaſſe, untill it returne to God that gave it.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:43024:35"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>The third Priviledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, If God be our Father, and we his children, then are we ſure of paternity and fatherhood; we are ſure of a Father, though departed this life; we are ſure of friends, and patrons, though gone before us; and it may be their affections gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; we have a provident, and able Father in heaven, though we be here many of us forlorne and forſaken, and none cares for us; which makes Chriſt give that Cordiall to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, when he left them (as ſheep amongſt Wolves) <hi>I go to my Father, and to your Father, &amp;c.</hi> And though you wander up and down on earth as pilgrims and ſtrangers, as all your Fathers were, yet in Heaven you ſhall have a Father and an inheritance which cannot be taken from you.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>I goe,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>to prepare you a place, and in my Fathers houſe,</hi> (who by my merits I have made yours) <hi>are many Manſions:</hi> manſions <hi>à manendo,</hi> from continuing, for we have no continuing City here, but we looke for one to come: Houſes I confeſſe we have, as Foxes have their holes, and Birds their neſts, and Beaſts their Dennes, quickly to be turned out of them: But in Heaven are eternall and everlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons prepared for Gods children.</p>
            <p>Here (in this ſtrange Countrey) we have hunger, and want, and neceſſity enough, but in our Fathers houſe we ſhall have plenty and abundance; we ſhall doe well therefore (with him) having ſuch ill uſage here to reſolve: <hi>I will goe to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> A bleſſed thing it is we have a Father to go to, <hi>tam pater nemo, tam pius nemo,</hi> This was <hi>Davids</hi> comfort, when Father and Mother forſook him, God tooke him up: <hi>when my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. Againe, <hi>I was poor and needy, and the Lord cared for me;</hi> And indeed this Father God forſakes none, untill he be forſaken, if he doe then; for I am ſure he raines his bleſſings unto the mouths of them that are open to blaſpheme him: Againe, <hi>David</hi> tells us, that when his people were hungry and thirſty, and their ſoules fainted in them, when being in this caſe, they cryed unto God in their trouble, he delivered them out of their diſtreſſe, he brought them forth into a wealthy place, ſet their feet in a large roome, and when they wanted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>read, gave them bread enough; He rained Manna, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43024:35"/> Quailes, and feathered foules as the duſt of the earth: was beſt to them in the worſt times, and when they were bad enough to him (God knowes) murmured and complained, even when their mouthes were filled and ſtuffed with plenty.</p>
            <p>And for his owne particular he tells us, that after many ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible experiments of Gods mercy and loving kindneſſe, his mighty and conſtant protection, and prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dence (in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation) all the dayes of his life, when the hands of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were ready to ſtone him, and deſtroy him (they knew not why) then <hi>David</hi> com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted himſelf in his God, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. And in the 23. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> he thankfully acknowledges, that in his greateſt extremity and need, and in the moſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rren place (the Wilderneſſe) God ſpread him a Table, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and filled his Cup. And the children of <hi>Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> Gods choſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n and children, with whom he had made a covenant, when they were all at the red Sea (at the very brink of deſtruction) and when there was but a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p between them and death, whom he had led as a Father his children by the hand, in the day time by a pillar of a cloud, and in the night by a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llar of fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, guiding him by the ſpeciall providence; ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d himſelfe a carefull and powerfull Father indeed, who when the earth denyed them bread) rained it upon them from Heaven as duſt, and feathered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I ſaid, <hi>as the ſand of the Sea</hi> &amp;c. when they were not only thus miraculouſly ſupplyed in their hunger, but in their thirſt brak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and clave the rocks, and gave them water out of the rocks as out of a River; cloathed them with garments which waxed not old, but endured without mending or wearing 40 yeares, made great and mighty Kings to give them room, and the Sea to give them way; I ſay againe, when they were in this great ſtreight, and exigence beyond all hope and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deliverance; before them the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a roaring, behind them <hi>Pharoah</hi> (the cruell tyrant) rageing and following them with a mind ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to deſtroy them: on each ſide the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls and Mountains inacceſſible: Then I ſay againe, did they pray unto the Lord in their trouble, and he delivered them, &amp;c. and they did ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord, in their ſudden and unex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pected delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: <hi>Neceſſitas humana, opportunitas divina,</hi> mans neceſſity is Gods opportunity, and then doth God commonly lay to his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43024:36"/> hand, when all other hopes and expectations of any aſſiſtance from the arme of fleſh are paſt: Who would not honour ſuch a Father, that honours them that honour him? He that ſerveth me, him will my Father honour, who would not honour ſuch a Father, and truſt in ſuch a God, who ſo undeſervedly digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and ſo mightily defends and preſerves, and ſo carefully and indulgently provides for them?</p>
            <p>If then he be our Father, let us give him our honour, and if our Maſter, our feare; This is that he calls for by his Prophets, and preſſes it ſtrongly and powerfully. 1. By way of conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>A Son honoureth his Father,</hi> &amp;c. 2. By way of exprobra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or redargation: If I be a Father where, &amp;c. as if he had ſaid, I will be neither Father nor Maſter to them that will not give me honour or feare: But now this very terme of paternity and Fatherhood, and the thought of theſe tranſcendent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, 1. That he preſerves us from ſinne. 2. That he purchaſes an immortal and glorious inheritance for us in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. 3. That (as a Father) he leads us through all the change and chances of this life, ſhould the more ſtir us up to conſtant filiall and univerſall obedience; At all times to ſerve him, who at all times and turnes (every day houre and minute) ſerves us, cheerfully to ſerve him in reverence and feare, and whoſe eye is on us and over us, and whoſe promiſe is richly and liberally to remunerate our ſhort ſervice, and imperfect obedience into our boſome. This was a ſpur to <hi>Moſes</hi> faithfulneſſe, he had an eye to the recompence of reward, and it is a part of the Catechiſme and Creed, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> taught the Hebrews, to believe that God is a plentifull rewarder of them that ſerve him: Without this hope and faithfull aſſurance, a man can performe but a dull and faint obedience and ſervice to God, therefore Chriſt made it a motive, not onely againſt diſtruſt and carefulneſſe, but to ready, diligent, and faithfull obedience: <hi>If an earthly Father knowes how to give,</hi> &amp;c. Thus we ſee the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable relation we are inveſted with, in our regeneration we have God for our Father, we ſee our honour and priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and let this ſerve for them, and for the firſt doctrine, That the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a new geniture and birth.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the ſecond, that God himſelf is the Author
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43024:36"/> and cauſe of this Birth. 11. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> begets us, It is the work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, his proper and principall, and peculiar worke; <hi>We are his workmanſhip,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>created to good workes, Gal.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
            <p>We ſay in Philoſophy, that <hi>Sol &amp; homo generant hominem,</hi> That the Sun with the help of Man, doth generate and beget a Man: But Chriſt alone, (the glorious Sunne of righteouſneſſe) begets us without the help of any Lunary or ſub-lunary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: we are not able of our ſelves, ſo much as to thinke a good thought towards our regeneration, how much le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e can we performe the worke: we cannot change a haire of our heads, much leſſe the frame of our hearts, or convert our ſelves. <hi>Convert us O Lord,</hi> cryes Jeremiah, <hi>and we ſhall be converted, chang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us, and we ſhall be changed:</hi> we cannot tell many times when we have grace, much leſſe can we affect it: No Man living can make a living Fly, much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe a living Soule, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall eſſence: It is God alone that formes and frames us after his own Image, which worketh in us both to will and to doe of his good pleaſure. <hi>We are begotten,</hi> ſaith John, <hi>not of Blood, nor of the will of Man, nor of the Fleſh but of the will of God:</hi> Not in any outward impure way of the fleſh, or in any carnall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as <hi>Nichodemus</hi> conceived, which is meant by Bloud and by the will of the Fleſh but by the will of God: It is the worke of the Spirit in which we are meerly paſſive, ask againe, we worke, being wrought upon: It is God that makes us, and not we our ſelves. But why then ſaith the Apoſtle, by the grace of God that is begotten in you; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 15. 'Tis true, Miniſters of the Goſpell may be called ſpirituall parents, and ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally to beget; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of our Sinnes, whom he begets in his bonds, ſo that many times the Word is full, when the Preacher is not, and runs when he cannot, <hi>Phil.</hi> 10. God uſeth ſometimes to pull that dignity and honour upon the inſtrumentall, which workes with him, and for him. As he g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves them (ſometimes) his own name, and calls them Gods, and accounts the neglect and diſeſteeme done to them, as done to him. So he ſometimes gives them his Sonnes name, calls them Saviours, <hi>Obadiah</hi> the laſt, <hi>I will raiſe up a Saviour ſaith God, in the last dayes;</hi> becauſe as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>By giving diligence to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43024:37"/> reading, exhortation and doctrine, he ſaves himſelfe,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 laſt. And in the <hi>Acts</hi> you read, that God daily added un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church (by the Miniſtery of the word) ſuch as ſhould be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 4 laſt. Thus (you ſee that God himſelfe is the Authour and cauſe of our new Birth, it is the proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar worke of God to beget, <hi>voluntariè nos genuit,</hi> of his will he beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te us. And yet you may pleaſe to obſerve, that as this act of regeneration is attributed to God the Father, as it is in this place: So ſometimes it is attributed to God the Sonne, as <hi>Eſai.</hi> 53. 10. <hi>Beleevers are called his ſeed, that he might ſee his ſeed, he made his ſoule a ſacrifice for ſinne:</hi> Sometimes to the ſpirit of God, as in <hi>Jo.</hi> 3 6. <hi>That which is borne of the fleſh, is fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, and the winde bloweth it, ſo is every one that is borne of the spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> It is God the Fathers will, he begets us of his will: Chriſt the Sonnes merit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 4. <hi>When the fulneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them that were under the Law, that we might receive the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption of the Sonne.</hi> God the Holy Ghoſts efficacy and power, by the Spirit of Gods ſanctifying and over-ſhadowing the Soule, the new Man is quickned and made; ſometimes it is attributed to all the three perſons in Trinity together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in that notable place, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 7. <hi>By his mercy he ſaved us, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt, which he abundantly ſhed in our hearts through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There we have the three perſons together in two verſes, and here all the cauſe of our regeneration in one, a parallel where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll hardly finde in the whole New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>But God (as I ſaid) he is the principall author and cauſe; His Miniſters but inſtrumentall: yet as his Miniſters, they are and may very well be called Fathers. And this near relation ſhould warme the hearts of Miniſters with an indulgent and paternall care and affection to beare great good will towards them, and (as <hi>Moſes</hi> is commanded) to carry them in his boſome: And as <hi>Aaron</hi> when he went up to pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to ſacrifice, he went up with the names of the twelve Tribes written upon his breaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> plate. So the Miniſters of the New Teſtament (the Paſtors of Chriſts Church) according to that Typ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ought to put up in all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, the prayers and ſupplications, the wants of his people, with his owne: As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls his people <hi>his Epiſtle written
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43024:37"/> in his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art;</hi> ſo ſhall the people be in their Paſtours. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> S. <hi>Pauls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ts deſire and prayer to Iſrael wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</hi> Indeed the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is nothing elſe but Jeſus Chriſts Letter, and Epiſtle writ from Heaven unto his Church; the mind of God expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Man by Chriſt, who ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the right hand of the Father, making thoſe Prayers and Petitions of ours which are imperfect in themſelves, to be more perfect by his mediation. And as theſe inſtruments of Regeneration are called Fathers both in the Old Teſtament, (<hi>My Father, my Father, &amp;c.</hi> cryes <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Elias, Jehoram</hi> to him, a wicked man, yet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had more grace than ſome have now, to call the Prophet his Father. (Worſe names now muſt be digeſted.)</p>
            <p>So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls them <hi>Nurſes,</hi> or <hi>Mothers</hi> too, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 7. There he put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon himſelfe the indulgence of a Mother, as afterward the affection of a Father, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 11. ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wing that as he did not occaſionally forget to uſe the gravity of a Father in his exhortations and inſtructions, ſo other whiles he puts upon him the meekneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſoftneſſe, and tenderneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a Mother, or of an affectionate Nurſe; Mothers and Nurſes having a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and fellow-feeling of their Childrens eſtates; the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowing by naturall inſtinct when the child is ſick, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, when it is diſtempered and pained, and will accordingly apply her ſelfe to give it eaſe, and not alwayes give it its hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, nor what it cryes for: So Gods Miniſters ſhould be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to free their people from diſtemper and diſorder, from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> corruption and error of the times, feeding them with wholſome and ſound doctrine, with the ſincere milk of the Word, that they may grow thereby, not with fancies and humours, and their owne inventions and imaginations, (for with griefe be it ſpoken, we are falne from the worſhipping of Images, to the worſhipping of Imaginations) which as it breeds ſickneſſes in young children to let them ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what they will, ſo it breeds fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and diviſions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xtreame diſtemperatures in States<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when they are ſuffered to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carryed about with every wind of doctrine, and every windy doctrine, (as the Iſraeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es by <hi>Aarons</hi> permiſſion and ſufferance worſhipped the Cllfe of their owne making.)</p>
            <p>And it teacheth the people againe, ſince they ſtand in ſo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43024:38"/> a relation to their Miniſters, (as Children to Parents) to carry a filiall and dutifull aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction towards their Paſtours, as they carry a loving, carefull, and paternall heart and eye towards them and their good. The want of which reciprocall loving kindneſſe and affection, when Father and Children, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſter and People, Maſter and Servant, have had a greater deſire to have their humours fed, than their ſoules edified, have not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſed great r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts and div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſions, (which with <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bens</hi> cauſed great gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efe and ſorrow of heart) but I dare ſay hath gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ved the bleſſed and holy Spirit of God, the ſole worker of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and <hi>by whom we are ſealed unto the day of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Spirit of God witneſſing to our spirits, that we are the ſons of God, Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this calls upon the great Fathers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who are called Gods, (being next to him) and <hi>Patres Patriae</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fathers of this Country<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay of the Common-wealth and State, to ſee with what meat their Children, their Subjects are fed: for as I ſaid, they are Paſtours and Fathers too. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> calls them <hi>Nurſing fathers,</hi> and <hi>Nurſing mothers,</hi> and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that in the great Reformation, Kings ſhould be nurſing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Queens nurſing mothers. That is, God would raiſe up the great Potentates and Princes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth, to provide that the people ſhould be fed with wholſome food, that living waters ſhould flow abundantly from the threſhold of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that all people ſhould know the Lord, from the greateſt to the leaſt.</p>
            <p>Hence it followes neceſſarily, that the Supreame Magiſtrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeaſoned with Religion, and what a ſweet perfume followes ſuch Princes, ſee in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xamples of <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, David, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aſa, Joſiah, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kiah, &amp;c.</hi> and not irreligious or Popiſhly affected, but ſoundly and firmly grounded, (for which we may bleſſe God) that he be a ſincere worſhipper, and ſerver of God, the feare of God being the beginning of wiſdome, and a man being never truly intelligent, untill he be obedient. The beſt Plot is to ſave a ſoule. For if that be true which they ſay in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is true and certaine, That what diſeaſe or infection the Nurſe hath, the ſucking child will partake of; and as the Parent is affected, ſo for the moſt part is the Childs inclination and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43024:38"/> Surely, and without all queſtion it will fare ſo in this: If God pleaſe to give us a Magiſtrate which is godly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, (and which he promiſeth to give to his people) Zealous and forward in the Duties of Chriſtianity, a lover and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the truth. Certainly, for the moſt part, the people will be ſo affected: That way which the Maſter Bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, all the reſt follow, and it is as true as old: <hi>Regis ad exemplum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Nothing is mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effectuall, or perſwaſive with the vulgar, than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and preſident of their Governors; who, if they be godly and religious, are notable meanes to draw men to Religion and Godlineſſe. <hi>Confeſſor Papa, Confeſſor populus</hi> (how true that is in the letter, let the world obſerve:) But ſurely where the Prince or Governor is a true Proteſtant, all will be of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; <hi>Joſuah</hi> is an excellent example and patterne for a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to walke by (and certainly his holineſſe made him without compare, ſucceſſefull in this life, and happy in the other) who in the midſt of an Idolatrous, froward, humorous and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh people, reſolves like a pious Ruler indeed, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord:</hi> walk others which way they will, I will walke this way, the way of Gods Commandements. When Religion, or (as into <hi>Zacheus</hi>) Salvation is entred into the great houſe, it cannot be long out of the little ones. Having ſpoke ſomething largely of our Father, let us ſpend a word or two about our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe there is great controverſie about her in the world; ſome repudiating her, ſome ſpitting in her face, ſome making her an Idoll and Puppet, ſome a Slut, ſome Nothing; I dare ſay moſt of the controverſies of this late age, have beene about dreſſing the Bride, ſome would have her a painted and gaudy Puppet; a finer Religion than the Proteſtants, as a vaine Lady once ſaid, ſome a homely Slut, without Forme and Beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, (as her Husband was accounted in the dayes of his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh) whereas, as God will be worſhipped of all in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith) in the beauty of holineſſe: ſo he would have comelineſſe and order, decency and beauty in his houſe. The ſpouſe of Chriſt being indeed black, but comely; ſomething obſcured in her Beauty by the morphew of Faction, and the Sun of Affliction, and the Tan of Perſecution, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable and lovely for all that: we are begotten (you ſee) and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43024:39"/> by whom, by God the Father, and by the Word of Truth: but of whom are we begotten? I anſwer, As God is our Father, ſo the Church is the Mother of us all, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 16. <hi>Of all the Children of God,</hi> ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Paul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Jeruſalem which is from above, is Free and Mother of us all: What is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> but the Church? For as the City was the Seate of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 5. ſo is the Church, the throne of Chriſt ſignified, and figured by the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>David, Rev.</hi> 3. 7. Therefore of both theſe God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes, <hi>here ſhall be my reſt for ever, Pſal.</hi> 132. And rightly and juſtly, is the Church called our Mother.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe her Maker is her Husband, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54. ſhe is the ſpouſe of our Father betroathed to him in Faith, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 19. I will marry thee unto me in Faith and Righteouſneſſe, coupled together and made one, by the unity and bond of the Spirit, Love being the matri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oniall bond: I am my Beloved, and my Beloved is mine, (he feeds among the Lillies) amongſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and Faithfull, not amongſt Bryars and Thorns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hemlock or Nettles.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, Becauſe we are children borne of her: This teacheth us to honour our Mother, and like little children, hang upon her breaſts for maintenance and ſuccour, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66. 14. Suck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolation, milke out and be delighted with the abundance of her glory: It is the Church, which by the bleſſing of God brings forth Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto God (by the Miniſtry of the word) as it is in my Text, <hi>he begets us by the word of truth.</hi> And if we be her children, we muſt feed of that milks, the word, which ſtill holds forth to us: <hi>As new born<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> babes,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 2.</p>
            <p>In a word, out of the Church there is no Salvation, who have not the Church for their Mother, ſhall not have God for their Father, was the ſaying of old; and good reaſon, for out of the Church, there are no meanes of Salvation: No word to teach, no Sacrament to confirme, no Prayer to bleſſe: But all theſe (and all other meanes) are in the wombe of the Church. It is here (and here onely) where the ſpirit of immortall ſeed begets grace, and holineſſe in the heart, and ſo a man is new borne, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. we are borne not of mortall, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Having God for our Father, and the Church for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43024:39"/> our Mother, we ought to be children of peace: For our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the God of peace, and our Saviour the Prince of peace, and the Goſpell a Goſpell of peace, and our Calling a Calling of peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. <hi>ut dixi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> It was the Harl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t would have the child divided, &amp;c. you know what Church it is that delights in blood, which make themſelves drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the Martyrs of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>They that are Gods children are of one minde, in one houſe, (and all believers are ſo as thoſe primitive were, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. the laſt.) They will not fall out becauſe they are Brethren, for we know it is a good and joyfull thing, &amp;c. But my ſheets ſwell to a bigger bulke than was intended, what is ſpoken therefore ſhall ſuffice for the proof and demonſtration of the two do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, out of the firſt cauſe of our Regeneration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a new geniture and birth, a new formation or Creation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That God himſelfeis the Author and cauſe of this Birth: He begets us, no farther have I gone, no farther dare I or will I goe, untill I ſee what entertainment theſe poore and unpoliſhed meditations ſhall receive in a froward and carping age. But yet out of theſe two doctrines, I ſhall deſire two things more to be obſered, for uſe and application. 1. The Chriſtians Dignity. 2. His Duty, and then I ſhall commit you to God and the Word of his Grace, the Word of Truth, which is able to build you farther, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 32.</p>
            <p>Firſt then for the Chriſtians dignity, which is three fold, To be regenerate and born againe.
<list>
                  <item>1. Dignity above men.</item>
                  <item>2. It is a dignity above the Angells.</item>
                  <item>3. It is a dignity above the Creatures; I will begin with the laſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a Dignity above the Creatures, for all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which God made have not his Image; but all that he doth bege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have: he made Man Lord, and Maſter of all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; he made them for Man, but Man himſelfe for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is a Dignity above all Men, the wicked have nothing to doe with this honour, (ſuch honour have all Gods, &amp;c.) none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſe. They are the Lords portion, his peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:43024:40"/> his firſt fruits. <hi>Iſrael is my firſt borne,</hi> Jer. 2. 2. <hi>The firſt fruits of my increaſe, Iſrael is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lineſſe to the Lord.</hi> They are his treaſure, the people that he onely looketh at and after, upon whom he ſets his love, his eyes are always upon them for good. <hi>The eye of the Lord is over the righteous, and his eares are open to their prayers,</hi> The World are his goods, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the round world, &amp;c. But they are his treaſure: and as where a mans treaſure is, there his heart will be: ſo is Gods heart upon his treaſure upon his ſecret ones, upon his peculiar. He writes them upon the palm of his hand, he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ales them upon his heart, they are as deare and near unto him as the Apple of his Eye; <hi>A book of remembrance is written for them that feare the Lord, Mal.</hi> 3. 16. God will certainly remember the ſervices of his children, and not forget the labour of their love, nor the good they doe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 10. Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as you you have heard, gives the <hi>Jewes</hi> an eminent and tranſcendent Title, having honoured them with theſe Denominations; a choſen generation, a royall Prieſthood, a holy Nation; he adds (what the Apoſtle here intimates) a peculiar people: <hi>populus acquiſitionis,</hi> a peculiar people.</p>
            <p>And two reaſons may be given of this appellation:</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are a peculiar people, becauſe God hath every way faſhioned them for himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe (as I told you) they are a peculiar people, or the firſt fruits of his creatures; ſet apart and conſecrate for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and worſhip. They are his treaſure, his onely treaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all he hath, the righteous comprehend all Gods gett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs: All other men are Gods creatures, but theſe are the firſt fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and as they are conſecrate to him, ſo they often conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate and bleſſe them: and (I am ſure) if they be not bettered by their converſation, they are bleſſed by their protection.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which is a bold aſſertion, it is a dignity above the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to be the ſons of God by regeneration, and to be redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Angels fell, he lets them lie in their fall, he reſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and keeps them in chaines of darkneſſe till the judgement. Man fell, and God preſently ſends him, nay gives him (by word of mouth) a promiſe of a Redeemer, That <hi>the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43024:40"/> &amp;c.</hi> So that God did more in our reſtauration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in our regeneration, than he did for the Angels of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To which of the Angels ſaid he, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee? He</hi> (that is, Chriſt) <hi>took not the ſeed of Angels, but the ſeed of Abraham.</hi> And again, <hi>He was made of the ſeed of David, Rom.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>He in no ſort took the ſeed of Abraham, Heb.</hi> 2. Chriſt (to fit himſelf for Mans ſalvation) took upon him an humane body, (the nature of Man) and in this kind dignified and honoured Mans n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ture above the Angels. And this (I dare ſay) ſeemeth to be a greater preheminence and dignity of the children of God above the Angels, in regard there is a neerer conju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct on between Chriſt and us, than between Chriſt and the Angels, (I meane in nature and perſon, not in place.) In place indeed the Angels are neerer unto God than Man, being in Heaven, and ſeeing the face of God, his glorious face; but in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the children of God are nearer than they are; for you have it expreſly ſaid, That <hi>Chriſt was made of the ſeed of David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Adde hereunto that he took upon him this ſeed in the womb of the bleſſed Virgin in his Incarnation, ſo that by his Conception and Incarnation, he was made one with us, and we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th him. And why did he take our nature upon him, and not ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature onely, but the contumelies of our nature, (ſo baſe and meane that they are not to be named) why did he this, but to redeeme us that were loſt, when our fall in <hi>Adam</hi> made us liable to eternall death, and left every mothers child of us in the merit and guilt of condemnation? <hi>When he took upon him to deliver Man, he did not abhor the Virgins womb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the Virgins womb was not ſo pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e or cleane a plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but the glorious and great God might have abhorred and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed it, (but when he took upon him to deliver Man, he did not.) Bleſſed be his Name therefore, who was borne that we might not die, who was made the Son of Man, that we might be made the ſons of God. <hi>Ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Filius Dei factus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt homo, ut ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines faceret filios Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde hereunto, that the Angels of Heaven deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e earneſtly to look into this myſterie of our Redemption, and doe attend it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 11. it doth them good at the heart to ſee their places
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43024:41"/> filled and ſupplyed by men, from which the evill Angels by their Apoſtaſie and pride fell.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (to honour the Regenerate yet farther) the Angels are charged and commanded to attend and wait upon them, <hi>He hath given his Angels charge over thee, &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 91. 11. They are not onely Fellow-ſervants with the Angels (as <hi>Iohn</hi> the Divine calls them) but they are ſervants to the children of God, for it is ſaid, <hi>They are miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to them that are heires of ſalvation, Heb.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have you ſeen the dignity of the Regenerate, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative honour of the children of God in ſome kind above the Angels. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt took not the ſeed or nature of Angels, but the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> (men ſubject to infirmities.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was conceived in the womb of a Virgin, and in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time made of a woman, and made under the Law, &amp;c. So that by his bleſſed Incarnation he is made one with us, and we with him; he ſits at the right hand of his Father glorified and bleſſed in our nature: <hi>Vexit in coelum carn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m noſtram, &amp;c.</hi> He took our fleſh into Heaven with him, as the pledge and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his love and favour, and hath ſent downe his Spirit unto us, as the pledge and ſeale of his love. Now <hi>Gloria capitis eſt sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> corporis,</hi> The glory of the Head is the Members hope; and if the Head be crowned, the whole Body is honoured.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The glorious Angels, and them bleſſed Spirits in heaven, deſire to look into the myſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Redemption, and indeed they themſelves receive ſome benefit by it, for they are thereby confirmed, that they cannot fall.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Angels are commanded to be our Guardians and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours. Never had any King or Prince ſuch Protectours as the ſons of God have: For the heavenly Angels pitch their tent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34: 11. and they have charge given them (of their Father which is in heaven) to bear them up in their hands, that they daſh not their feet againſt a ſtone. Oh how fearfull ſhould we be to offend, having ſuch eyes over us, and ſuch hands under us, and ſuch glorious ſpirits about us! Who cannot but admire the great love and mercy of God, in the words of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, Lord what is man? Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Thou madeſt him little lower</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:43024:41"/> (in ſome degrees higher) <hi>than the Angels, and haſt crowned him with dignity and honour:</hi> And in the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld we love the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Well, conſidering our tranſcendent and high D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnity, let us obſerve now ſome duties yet; for ſurely that God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſo much honours us, we ought by ſome duty to give him the honour due unto his name. Since he hath done ſo much for us, let us doe ſomething for him, namely, give him our homage and ſervice; for Chriſt will be a Jeſus and Saviour to none, but to ſuch to whom he is a Lord and King: <hi>Magnes amoris am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r:</hi> The load-ſtone of Love, is Love, and <hi>Durus eſt qui amorem non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendet,</hi> He is hard-harted, who will not returne Love for Love.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then let us do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing to make our heavenly Father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of us: <hi>It is not for Kings O Lemuel, it is not for Kings to drinke wine, nor Princes ſtrong drinke, Prov.</hi> 31. 2. It b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeems not Saints to be ſinners, it becomes not us to call God Father, as the Jewes called Chriſt King, and ſpit in his face and revile him: You know how <hi>Jacob</hi> chid and reproved his Sonnes, comming from the murther of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mites. You have made my name to ſtinke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gen.</hi> 34. the laſt. <hi>Num est haec tunica fratris veſtri,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jacob</hi> to his Sonnes) <hi>Is this your brothers coat?</hi> Is it the Livery and guiſe of Brethren of the Sonnes of God to be hard-harted, and cruelly minded, one towards another? When <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſtabbed in the Senat houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> he cryes out unto <hi>Brutus,</hi> what wilt thou my Sonne? as if he had ſaid, The cruelty of others I regard not, I care not for ſo much but for (<hi>Brutus</hi>) my adopted Sonne, one whom I have made my heire, for thee to lift up thy hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. <hi>O hold thy hand, thou killeſt me without a blow.</hi> So for <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Pagans, Turkes</hi> and <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and ſuch as were heard of Chriſt, for ſuch to deny and blaſpheme him, and ſo ſhoote out their arrowes, oathes are bitter words (as they ſay the <hi>Indians</hi> doe at the Sun becauſe they feel no heat of it at noone day) it is not ſo much: But for Chriſtians, for profeſſed Chriſtians, ſuch as call God Father, to abuſe the name of their Father in curſing and ſwearing, and fearfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, and lyes, and perjuries, how unfit and uncongruous is it to them?</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:43024:42"/>
            <p n="2">2. If we be the children of God, we will meekly beare our heavenly Fathers corrections, we will as I ſaid, kiſſe his rodde and embrace his chaſtiſements upon our knees: for if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure chaſtening, and deale with us as with Sonnes, for what Sonne, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 7. There is no Sonne whom the Father chaſtiſeth not. Even the beloved Sonne (the Sonne in whom he was pleaſed) was <hi>Vir dolorum</hi> the man of ſorrow, and one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in infirmity: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicum Deus habet filium ſine peccato, nullum ſine flagello:</hi> God had one Sonne without ſinne, but never had he Sonne without ſorrow; even Chriſt the Sonne of Gods love, and of his deſires, <hi>Qui peccatum non novit, Qui pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum non fecit,</hi> He that knew no ſinne, nor did no ſinne, knew ſorrow enough from his Cradle to his Croſſe, from his Birth to his Grave, and he learnt (and taught) us obedience by thoſe things he ſuffered (although he was the Sonne.) Now ſhall the Generall ſuffer, nay bleed, and ſhall we that fight (or at leaſt pretend we fight) under his banner goe free? ſhall the head ſuffer, and the Members ſcape? No<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>pudeat membrum deliciari ſub capite ſpinis coronato,</hi> It is a ſhame for the members to ſpor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and play under the head, which was crowned with Thornes. A delicate and fine member, doth not well agree with a crucified head. If then the world crowne Chriſt with Thornes, ſhall we thinke it will crowne us with Flowers? If it Crucified Chriſt, do we thinke it will glorifie us? No, he that is exempted from the number of them that are corrected, he is exempted from the number of Sonnes; and they are not Sonnes but Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom our heavenly Father chaſtiſeth not: <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Afflictions are ſure evidences of our ſactification.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If God be our Father, and we his children, let us live as alwayes in Gods preſence, and ſo living feare to offend him: we muſt obſerve this towards our naturall and civill parents, that we dare not offend b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore their face: No man will ſteale in the face of his judge, who hath power &amp; authority to puniſh him, and (fools as we are) do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dare commit ſinne in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our heavenly Father, commit any evill in his ſight, who will certainly bring every work into judgement, &amp;c. we dare do that in the face of Heaven, which we dare not doe if a child ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. It was a holy practice of <hi>David, I ſet the Lord alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43024:42"/> my eyes, therefore I ſhall not fall:</hi> And it was <hi>Aſephs</hi> holy and pious reſolution, <hi>How can I doe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. It is (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion) a ſtrong Bit and Bridle to reſtraine the moſt licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and wicked man living from ſinne, when he conſiders that he ſees him that ſhall judge him, and that he acts and does all under his Fathers eye: <hi>God is in this place,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jacob, and I was not aware of it,</hi> ſo God ſees us, though we will not ſee it nor know it: <hi>Went not my heart with thee whilst thou wentest after Naaman for a bribe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Gehezi,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. So go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not Gods eyes with us, whilſt we goe into ſuch and ſuch places, and about ſuch and ſuch ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere locum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſeeke out if you can, O ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a place where God ſees you not, and ſinne and ſpare not. But if Gods eyes be in every place, his 7. eyes goe throughout the world. As a well-drawn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> picture (which ſeems to eye all in the room) God lookes upon and beholds all the world. <hi>Cave quid agas Deus t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Take we heed what we doe for God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ees us, and what need we care, if no man ſees us doing any evill, when he ſees us that ſhall Judge us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If God be our Father, and we his Children, let us often pray unto our heavenly Father, fall upon our knees and aske him bleſſing: we expect this, and teach it our children daily to crave our bleſſing; ſhall we expect, and deſire that from our children, which we will not doe to God? looke that our children ſhould doe it daily to us, and we doe it ſo ſeldome to him. God loves to ſee us daily and conſtant ſuppliants, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us upon our knees; and if we know not how to pray as we ought, his ſpirit will helpe our infirmities, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. He that bids us take words into our mouths, puts words into our mouthes, and bids us ſay no more than this in faith and full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance (or to this effect) Take away our iniquity, and receive us graciouſly.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object, what needs words, ſince our heavenly Father knowes whereof we have need (as Chriſt ſaith) before we aske, what need words to God, who knowes the ſecrets of all hearts, and tell us by his Prophets: <hi>Antequam clametis ego exaudiam,</hi> Before you call or cry I will heare; and <hi>David</hi> did but cry, he would confeſſe his iniquity, and God forgave him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43024:43"/> his ſinne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. It is true, 1. God needs no words, but we doe, to ſtir up our hearts and affections to God: and 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would have us take ſhame and confuſion to our ſelves. 3. He hath given us our tongues as Inſtrments to glorifie him, and therefore God will have our glory, our tongue (as <hi>David</hi> calls it and often awakens it) uſed in our Petition and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, our affections and deſires are the more inkindled and freed by words, and Gods graces are excited by prayer. And though God knowes the heart, yet he will leave the hid M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of the heart manifeſted to man, for his edification and example. 4. Beſides God will be glorified by the inward as well as by the outward Man, he made both, and redeemed both, and therefore will be glorified with both. By Prayer we entertaine Familiarity with our heavenly Father, it is the language of the Saints, yea his Childrens Dialect, ſuch a prevailing language it is, that it ever prevailes, and is never ſent empty away: what was vaine gloriouſly ſpoken by a Kings Favorite, may be truly ſpoken of the King of Kings, God can deny prayer nothing: It is the hand that takes any thing out of Gods treaſury, it is the Key that opens Heaven, by it <hi>Elias</hi> opened and ſhut Heaven as his private cheſt: There is much ſpoken of it, that I can adde nothing but a deſire to learne to be ſo well exerciſed in it, (as ſome as have wrote very worthily of it) onely give me leave from a Father to ſay thus much of it: It is, <hi>Deo ſacrificium, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranti ſubſidium, Diab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo flagellum,</hi> A ſacrifice to God, who ſtileth himſelfe a God that heareth prayers, a ſuccour to the Soule, and therefore <hi>to thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) ſhall all fleſh come:</hi> It is a ſcourge to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vill, for as one well, <hi>Gravis aequidem nobis eſt illius tentatio, ſed longe illi gravior noſtri ratio:</hi> His temptations are griaevous to us, but our prayers are more grievous to him, what ſhall I ſay? If we pray unto God, he accounts it a deſert, and if we praiſe him, a reward; he that will not give thus much (or rather thus little) to his heavenly Father, deſerves nothing at all from him: For Rivers of Gods goodneſſe, let us give him ſome drops of our thankfulneſſe, and follow him with our prayers, who followes us with his bleſſings. This is all he requires at our hands, who receive all from him.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:43024:43"/>
            <p>Laſtly, if God be our Father, and we his children, Let us as Chriſt counſels us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. and God commands us <hi>Caſt our care upon him,</hi> (for he careth for us) and hath given his word five times in his holy Book, That <hi>he will never faile us nor forſake us.</hi> Which for the comfort and confidence of Gods children is ſo often preſſed and repeated, <hi>Whoſoever truſts in God,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid) wants nothing that is good;</hi> and he ſpeaks it by his owne experience, <hi>I have been young, &amp;c.</hi> Reade the 6. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and you ſhall ſee there, how our Saviour chides and reproves the diffidence and diſtruſt of his children, by ſending them to the fowles of the aire the graſſe in the field, the ſparrowes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe top, to the ravens and lillies &amp;c. A ſparrow, nay a haire of our heads falls not to the ground without Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. <hi>Et ſi ſic curat ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lua, in quanta ſecuritate est anima</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> If God care thus much for our ſuperfluous things, in what great ſecurity and ſafety are our ſoules! And if he feeds the young Ravens that call upon him, will he not much more feed you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O ye of little faith? Certainly he that provides meat for the fowles of the aire, will cauſe the fowles of the aire to provide meat for Man, before he ſhall ſtarve or want. And he that clothes the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llies of the field with a far more gloriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mantle than ever covered the corps of <hi>Solomon;</hi> ſhall he not much ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner cloathe you? &amp;c. We profeſſe that we reſt upon God and truſt in him for remiſſion of ſins, for the reſurrection of the body, and life everlaſting: Certainly (for concluſion) I ſhall never beleeve that thoſe perſons doe or can truſt in God for theſe ſpirituall bleſſings, who will not truſt him for a piece of bread, or lock of wooll. Caſt therefore your care upon God, who hath begot you by his Word, and feed upon that Word, and let that Word feed you. <hi>Man liveth not by bread alone &amp;c. Vita vera eſt vita fidei,</hi> The true life is the life of faith, and <hi>the Juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi> Truſt in the Lord, and be doing of good, walk diligently and carefully in your callings, and you ſhall be fed. <hi>David</hi> ſpake it by experience, <hi>I was poore and needy, &amp;c.</hi> Truſt I ſay in him, commit thy ſelfe to him, and he will bring it to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Surely if men that are evill, know how to give good gifts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their children, (and a bad man may be a good father) ſhall
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43024:44"/> not the God of all comfort and conſolation, the Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, provide for us? Yes, God hath given his Word, (and good is the Word of the Lord, or the Lord will be as good as his word) (in which word let us reſt and repoſe) <hi>I will never faile nor forſake thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus if we beare filiall and dutifull reſpects to our heavenly Father, who hath begotten us to an inheritance immortall, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and which fadeth not away, 1. By being obedient to him, 2. By doing nothing to make him aſhamed of us, 3. By meekly bearing his chaſtiſements, 4. By living in his preſence, and ſo living in feare to offend him, 5. By daily praying unto God, for by daily praying we ſhall learne to love and to feare him: Laſtly, by relying and depending upon him for all things neceſſary both for body and ſoule: when we ſhall goe hence to be no more ſeene, we ſhall goe to our Father, receive and obtaine the inheritance of ſons, and be welcommed with that bleſſed <hi>Venite</hi> of Chriſt our Judge and elder Brother, <hi>Come ye bleſſed children of my Father, inherit, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 25.</p>
            <closer>To which Kingdome, he for his Name ſake bring us, which ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought us, and that Kingdome for us, Jeſus Christ the righteous. To whom with the Father and the bleſſed Spirit, be all honour, praiſe, power, might, majeſty and domonion, now and for evermore. <hi>AMEN, AMEN.</hi>
            </closer>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43024:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
